[{ "id" : 1, "question" : "Who is the person fondly known as the Chief Architect of the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : " Dr. B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "First attempt in world to constitute a Constituent Assembly to frame a Constitution was made by ", "answer" : " America  "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "The first attempt by Indians to write a Constitution to India was done by a Committee headed by Motilal Nehru, which is known  as ", "answer" : " Nehru Report  "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "The idea of the Constitution of India was flashed for the first time by ", "answer" : " M. N. Roy "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "The plan of setting up of a Constituent Assembly to draw up the future Constitution for India was given by ", "answer" : " The Cabinet Mission Plan  "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "The members of the Constituent Assembly were ", "answer" : " Elected by Provincial Assemblies "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "Which of the following word was added into the Preamble of the Constitution by the 42nd Amendment Act, 1976? ", "answer" : " Socialist  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "From which Constitution was a concept of a 5-year plan borrowed into our Constitution? ", "answer" : " USSR  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "The procedure of Amendment to the Constitution is borrowed from the Constitution Of ", "answer" : " South Africa  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "Which country is the best example for the Federal and Unitary Governments? ", "answer" : " America and Britain  "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "Which of the following is not a Democratic Institution of the Rig Vedic era? ", "answer" : " Grama "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "During Medieval India, which kings first established ‘Local Self Government’? ", "answer" : " Cholas "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "The East India Company was established in the year ", "answer" : " 1600 "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "Which Charter empowered the British Governors of Presidencies to make Bye-Laws, Rules, Regulations in conformity with the British laws? ", "answer" : " Charter of  1726  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "Who started Dual Government in Bengal? ", "answer" : " Robert Clive "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "Who is the first Governor General of Bengal? ", "answer" : " Warren Hastings "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "Which is the first written document in the Constitutional History of India? ", "answer" : " The Regulating Act, 1773  "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "Which Act created for the first time in India ‘Government of India’? ", "answer" : " Charter Act of 1833  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "Which Act created for the first ‘The Supreme Court’? ", "answer" : " The Regulating Act, 1773 "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "First Law Commission was appointed in India for codification of laws under the Chairmanship of ", "answer" : " Lord Macaulay  "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "Which Act made the beginning of a Parliamentary System in India? ", "answer" : " Charter Act of 1853  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "Under which of the following Act, the Crown of England took the affairs of the Government of India into its own hands? ", "answer" : " Government of India Act, 1858  "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "The Governor General of India was also the representative of British Crown to Princely States in India and hence was known as the ", "answer" : "Viceroy of India  "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "Which Act for the first time gave an opportunity for Indians to enter into the sphere of Legislature? ", "answer" : " Indian Councils Act, 1861  "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "Which Act made the beginning of Electoral System in India? ", "answer" : " Government of India Act, 1858  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Which of the following Act made the Indian Legislature Bi-cameral for the first time? ", "answer" : " Government of India Act, 1919  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "The famous Dandi March laid by Gandhiji was against ", "answer" : " Salt Tax "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "Which proposal was referred as ‘Post Dated Cheque’? ", "answer" : "The Cripps Proposal "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "Indian National Congress started ‘Quit India Movement’ after the failure of ", "answer" : " Cripps Mission  "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "Gandhiji gave a call to all Indians ‘Do or Die’, which is popularly known as ", "answer" : " Quit India Movement  "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "Which Plan rejected the demand for the independent Pakistan? ", "answer" : " Cabinet Mission Plan "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Partition of British India into two independent nations India and Pakistan was done according to ", "answer" : " Mountbatten Plan  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "The Federal features of the Indian Government was introduced by the ", "answer" : " Government of India Act, 1935  "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "Which feature was borrowed by the Indian Constitution from the British Constitution? ", "answer" : " Law making procedure, Parliamentary System of Government,  Rule of law  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "The Constitution supports ", "answer" : " Rule of Law "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "In Britain, Parliament is supreme; accordingly which among the following is supreme in India? ", "answer" : " Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "The Government of India Act 1935 provided for ", "answer" : " Establishment of Federal Court, Diarchy at Center, Provincial autonomy  "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "The Act of 1935 abolished ", "answer" : " Diarchy in the Provinces "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "The Constitution of India was enacted by a Constituent Assembly set up ", "answer" : " Under the Cabinet Mission Plan, 1946  "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "The Constituent Assembly of India was created as per the proposal of ", "answer" : " Cabinet Mission  "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "In which year did the Cripps Mission come to India? ", "answer" : "1942 "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "The Constituent Assembly set up under the Cabinet Mission Plan had a strength of ", "answer" : "389 "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "The strength of the Constituent Assembly, after the withdrawal of the Muslim League, was reduced to ", "answer" : " 299  "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "How many Committees were set up by the Constituent Assembly for framing the Constitution? ", "answer" : " 13  "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "Who of the following acted as the Constitutional Advisor to the Constituent Assembly? ", "answer" : "B. N. Rau  "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "Demand for a Constitution, framed by a Constituent Assembly was made by ", "answer" : "Gandhiji "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "The idea of a Constituent Assembly to frame a Constitution for India was first mooted by ", "answer" : " Swaraj Party in 1928  "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "Who started with presentation of the ‘Objective Resolution’ on 22.01.1947? ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru  "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "When was the ‘Objective Resolution’ moved and adopted? ", "answer" : "13.12.1946 and 22.01.1947  "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "The Members of the Constituent Assembly were ", "answer" : " Elected by Provincial Assemblies "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "The Constituent Assembly of India held its first meeting on ", "answer" : " 09.12.1946 "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "Which one of the following acted as the Provisional President of the Constituent Assembly? ", "answer" : " Sachidananda Sinha  "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "The Constituent Assembly elected on 11.12.1946 as its Permanent Chairman ", "answer" : " Rajendra Prasad  "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "Who elected the Chairman of the Drafting Committee of the Constituent Assembly? ", "answer" : " B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "The Chairman of the Drafting Committee to prepare a Draft Constitution of India was ", "answer" : " B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "The name of Dr. B. R. Ambedkar is associated with which of the following? ", "answer" : " Chairman-Drafting Committee  "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "Who among the following was   member of the Drafting Committee? ", "answer" : "Ambedkar, Gopalachari Ayyangar, Alladi Krishnaswami  "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "Many Provisions in our Constitution have been borrowed from the Government of  India Act ", "answer" : "  1919  "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "The Government of India Act 1919 introduced a system of diarchy in the provinces. ‘Diarchy’ means a system of ", "answer" : "Double government  "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "When was the Constituent Assembly established to form the Constitution? ", "answer" : "   06.12.1946 "},
{ "id" : 61, "question" : "The Constitution of India was adopted on ", "answer" : " 26.11.1949 "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "The Constitution of India came into force on ", "answer" : "   26.01.1950 "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "The Constitution of India contains (Articles, Parts, Schedules) ", "answer" : "444, 24, 12 "},
{ "id" : 64, "question" : "How much time did the Constituent Assembly take to prepare the Constitution of India? ", "answer" : "02Y, 11M, 18D  "},
{ "id" : 65, "question" : "Who had given the idea of a Constitution for India of all? ", "answer" : "   M. N. Roy "},
{ "id" : 66, "question" : "The Constitution of India is ", "answer" : " written and bulky document "},
{ "id" : 67, "question" : "The Constitution framed by a Committee consisting of the people representatives is called as ", "answer" : " Written Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 68, "question" : "Constitution which provides for a series of semi-autonomous states joined together as a  nation is ", "answer" : " Federal Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 69, "question" : "Centralization of power is an important feature in ", "answer" : " Federal Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 70, "question" : "The Constitution which can be amended by simple act of the legislature is known as ", "answer" : "    Flexible Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 71, "question" : "Which one of the following provisions of the Constitution came into force soon after its  adoption on 26.11.1949? ", "answer" : " Provisional Parliament,  Provisions relating to Citizenship,   Elections  "},
{ "id" : 72, "question" : "India has been described under Article 1 of the Constitution as a ", "answer" : " Union of States  "},
{ "id" : 73, "question" : "The Constitution of India is ", "answer" : " Partly rigid and partly flexible  "},
{ "id" : 74, "question" : "The Constitution of India describes India as ", "answer" : "   A Union of States  "},
{ "id" : 75, "question" : "The Indian Constitution is recognized as ", "answer" : "    Federal in form and Unitary in spirit  "},
{ "id" : 76, "question" : "The feature common of both Indian and American Federation is ", "answer" : " Supreme Court to  interpret Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 77, "question" : "The Indian Constitution came into force on 26.01.1950, hence this day is celebrated as ", "answer" : "  Republic Day   "},
{ "id" : 78, "question" : "January 26th was selected as the date for the inauguration of the Constitution because ", "answer" : "    Congress had observed it as the Independence Day in 1930  "},
{ "id" : 79, "question" : "26th November, 1949 is a significant day in our constitutional history because ", "answer" : " The  Constitution was adopted on this day  "},
{ "id" : 80, "question" : "Which one of the following exercised the most profound influence on the Indian  Constitution?", "answer" : "The GoI Act, 1935  "},
{ "id" : 81, "question" : "The Parliamentary system of Government in India is based on the pattern of ", "answer" : " Great  Britain   "},
{ "id" : 82, "question" : "To whom does the People of India gave the Constitution to ", "answer" : " Themselves  "},
{ "id" : 83, "question" : "The beginning word ‘WE’ in the Preamble refers to the ", "answer" : " Citizens of India  "},
{ "id" : 84, "question" : "The important test to identify the basic features of the Indian Constitution is ", "answer" : " Preamble  "},
{ "id" : 85, "question" : "The Preamble to the Constitution contain ", "answer" : "   Fraternity, Democratic, Sovereignty  "},
{ "id" : 86, "question" : "India is a Sovereign Socialist Secular Democratic Republic. In the Indian Constitution, this  expression occurs in ", "answer" : "Preamble  "},
{ "id" : 87, "question" : "The Preamble to the Constitution declares India as ", "answer" : "Sovereign Socialist Secular  Democratic Republic  "},
{ "id" : 88, "question" : "The Preamble of Indian Constitution has been amended so far  ", "answer" : "Once   "},
{ "id" : 89, "question" : "The Preamble was amended by the ", "answer" : "42nd Amendment, 1976  "},
{ "id" : 90, "question" : "‘Fraternity’ means ", "answer" : "   spirit of brotherhood  "},
{ "id" : 91, "question" : "The words ‘Socialist Secular’ were ", "answer" : "   Added by the 42nd Amendment  "},
{ "id" : 92, "question" : "‘Liberty’ in our Preamble does not include Freedom of ", "answer" : "   Action  "},
{ "id" : 93, "question" : "Which among the following is an aid to the Statutory Interpretation? ", "answer" : "Preamble   "},
{ "id" : 94, "question" : "Which of the key to open the minds of the makers of the Constitution? ", "answer" : " Preamble  "},
{ "id" : 95, "question" : "If the Head of the State is an elected functionary for a fixed term, it is known as ____State.  ", "answer" : "Republic  "},
{ "id" : 96, "question" : "The Preamble to the Indian Constitution is borrowed from the ", "answer" : " Objective Resolution  "},
{ "id" : 97, "question" : "Objective Resolution was silent as to the concept of ____ which was inserted into the  Preamble by the Constituent Assembly ", "answer" : "Democratic  "},
{ "id" : 98, "question" : "Universal Adult Franchise shows that India is a _______ country. ", "answer" : " Democratic   "},
{ "id" : 99, "question" : "Who proposed Preamble before the Drafting Committee of the Constitution? ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru  "},
{ "id" : 100, "question" : "The Preamble of our Constitution reads ", "answer" : "   We, the people of India in our  Constituent Assembly adopt, enact and give to  "},
{ "id" : 101, "question" : "India is called a ‘Republic’ because ", "answer" : " The Head of the State in India (President) is  an elected head for a fixed period  "},
{ "id" : 102, "question" : "‘Sovereignty’ in a democracy rests with the ", "answer" : " People  "},
{ "id" : 103, "question" : "The Preamble secures Justice, Liberty, Equality and Fraternity to ", "answer" : " All citizens   "},
{ "id" : 104, "question" : "The Preamble of the Constitution indicates ", "answer" : "   The source of the Indian  Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 105, "question" : "It is not the objective enshrined in the Preamble. ", "answer" : " Secure shelter and proper  livelihood to all  "},
{ "id" : 106, "question" : "The idea of social, economic and political justice has been taken from _____ Revolution. - ", "answer" : " French  "},
{ "id" : 107, "question" : "The concept of equality and fraternity has been taken from _____ Revolution. ", "answer" : "  Russian  "},
{ "id" : 108, "question" : "Which of the following is described as the ‘Soul of the Constitution’? ", "answer" : " Preamble  "},
{ "id" : 109, "question" : "Which one of the following is not treated as part of the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Fundamental Duties  "},
{ "id" : 110, "question" : "Democracy of India rests on the fact that ", "answer" : " People have the right to choose and  change the government  "},
{ "id" : 111, "question" : "The word ‘Democracy’ is derived from the Greek words ", "answer" : " Demos and Kratos  "},
{ "id" : 112, "question" : "India opted for a Federal form of government because of ", "answer" : " Linguistic and Regional  Diversity  "},
{ "id" : 113, "question" : "What is the chief (ultimate) source of political power (authority) in India?", "answer" : "People  "},
{ "id" : 114, "question" : "A Flexible Constitution ", "answer" : "   can be amended easily  "},
{ "id" : 115, "question" : "The Judiciary acts as an guardian of the Constitution in a ", "answer" : " Federal government  "},
{ "id" : 116, "question" : "India is a Secular State because ", "answer" : " It is described so in the preamble of the  Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 117, "question" : "Our Constitution has laid emphasis on securing social, economic and political justice to all  the citizens of the country. These objectives are aimed at securing a ", "answer" : " Welfare State  "},
{ "id" : 118, "question" : "Modern States are generally considered as ", "answer" : " Welfare States  "},
{ "id" : 119, "question" : "A State which does not promote or interfere in the affairs of religion is referred to as ", "answer" : "  Secular  "},
{ "id" : 120, "question" : "The Constitution is a ", "answer" : " Dynamic Law   "},
{ "id" : 121, "question" : "The Constitution of India provides ", "answer" : " Single citizenship   "},
{ "id" : 122, "question" : "The Constitution provides ", "answer" : " Powers, Responsibilities, Limitations  "},
{ "id" : 123, "question" : "The fundamental organs of the State are established by ", "answer" : " Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 124, "question" : "Detailed provisions regarding acquisition and termination of Indian citizenship are  contained in ", "answer" : " Act passed by the Parliament in 1955   "},
{ "id" : 125, "question" : "Which of the following is not a condition for becoming an Indian citizen? [Citizenship by]  ", "answer" : " Acquiring property  "},
{ "id" : 126, "question" : "A person can lose citizenship through ", "answer" : " Deprivation, Termination, and  Renunciation  "},
{ "id" : 127, "question" : "The aims and objectives of the Constitution have been enshrined in ", "answer" : " The Preamble  "},
{ "id" : 128, "question" : "The Office of the Governor General of India was for the first time created under ", "answer" : "  Regulating Act, 1773   "},
{ "id" : 129, "question" : "According to the Act of 1858, the territory was divided into ", "answer" : " Provinces   "},
{ "id" : 130, "question" : "When did the British Crown assume sovereignty over India from East India Company?", "answer" : "   1858   "},
{ "id" : 131, "question" : "Morley-Minto Reforms were implemented by the Indian Councils Act ", "answer" : " 1909   "},
{ "id" : 132, "question" : "Which of the following is also known as the Act of 1919? ", "answer" : " Montague-Chelmsford  Reform Act   "},
{ "id" : 133, "question" : "Under which of the following Act was Provincial Autonomy introduced in India? ", "answer" : "  Government of India Act, 1935  "},
{ "id" : 134, "question" : "Who made the Constitution of India? ", "answer" : " The Constituent Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 135, "question" : "A Constituent Assembly is convened to ", "answer" : " Frame the Constitution of the country  "},
{ "id" : 136, "question" : "The Constituent Assembly was set up to under the ", "answer" : " Cabinet Mission Plan of 1946   "},
{ "id" : 137, "question" : "Which party was not associated with the Constituent Assembly of India? ", "answer" : " The  Communist Party   "},
{ "id" : 138, "question" : "The Republic of India established by the Constitution is ", "answer" : " Sovereign, Socialist,  Secular  "},
{ "id" : 139, "question" : "The mind and ideals of the framers of the Constitution are reflected in the ", "answer" : " Preamble   "},
{ "id" : 140, "question" : "In our Constitution, what justice is not given to the citizens? ", "answer" : " Technical   "},
{ "id" : 141, "question" : "The present Five-year Plan (2002-2007) is ", "answer" : " 11th   "},
{ "id" : 142, "question" : "‘Amend’ means ", "answer" : " remove the difficulties   "},
{ "id" : 143, "question" : "‘Enact’ means ", "answer" : " pass a law  "},
{ "id" : 144, "question" : "Who advocated ‘Grama Swarajya’ for the growth of the villages? ", "answer" : " Gandhiji   "},
{ "id" : 145, "question" : "‘Poornaswarajya’ was declared as the goal of the Congress on December 1929 in the ", "answer" : " Lahore Session   "},
{ "id" : 146, "question" : "Our Constitution prohibits _____", "answer" : "Untouchability   "},
{ "id" : 147, "question" : "The Constitution declared India as a Republic on ________ ", "answer" : " 26.01.1950   "},
{ "id" : 148, "question" : "Who has given the following statement: “Democracy means a Government of the people,  by the people and for the people”? ", "answer" : " Abraham Lincoln  "},
{ "id" : 149, "question" : "Which one of the following features was borrowed by the framers of the Constitution  from the US Constitution? ", "answer" : " Removal of Judges of the Supreme Court, Judicial  Review,  Fundamental Rights  "},
{ "id" : 150, "question" : "The ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity enshrined in the Preamble of the Constitution  were adopted under inspiration from ", "answer" : " The French Revolution  "},
{ "id" : 151, "question" : "_______is the chief force of political power in India. ", "answer" : " The People   "},
{ "id" : 152, "question" : "The Constitution describes the Indian Union as ", "answer" : " India i.e. Bharat   "},
{ "id" : 153, "question" : "The Constitution of India describes India as ", "answer" : " Union of States  "},
{ "id" : 154, "question" : "The two persons who played a vital role in the integration of Princely States were ", "answer" : "  Sardar Patel and V. P. Menon   "},
{ "id" : 155, "question" : "The States were reorganized on linguistic basis in ", "answer" : " 1956   "},
{ "id" : 156, "question" : "Which State enjoys the distinction of being the first linguistic State of India? ", "answer" : " Andhra  Pradesh  "},
{ "id" : 157, "question" : "The Indian Federal system is modeled on the Federal system of ", "answer" : " Canada   "},
{ "id" : 158, "question" : "India is known as Parliamentary Democracy because ", "answer" : " Executive is responsible to the  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 159, "question" : "The Indian State is regarded as federal because the Indian Constitution provides for ", "answer" : "  Sharing of power between Center and States  "},
{ "id" : 160, "question" : "In which Case did Supreme Court hold that the Preamble was a part of the  Constitution? ", "answer" : " Keshavananda Bharti Case  "},
{ "id" : 161, "question" : "In which Case did Supreme Court hold that Preamble was not a part of the Constitution? - ", "answer" : "  Berubari Case  "},
{ "id" : 162, "question" : "The Ninth Schedule ", "answer" : "  was added to the Constitution by the 1st Amendment  "},
{ "id" : 163, "question" : "Which Schedule details the boundaries of the States and the Union Territories? ", "answer" : "  I  "},
{ "id" : 164, "question" : "The details of salaries, allowances, etc. of the President, Vice President, Speaker, Judges  of Supreme Court, etc. are provided in Schedule ", "answer" : " II   "},
{ "id" : 165, "question" : "Which Schedule gives details regarding the subjects included in the three lists — Central,  State and Concurrent Lists? ", "answer" : "VII  "},
{ "id" : 166, "question" : "In the Indian Constitution ", "answer" : " There are three lists: The Union list, the State list and  the Concurrent list  "},
{ "id" : 167, "question" : "Which of the following statements is correct? ", "answer" : " Rule of Law is a basic feature of the  Constitution which cannot be amended under Article 368 of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 168, "question" : "As per Article 262 of Indian Constitution, disputes relating to waters shall be solved By ", "answer" : "Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 169, "question" : "Which one of the following declares India as a Secular State? ", "answer" : " Preamble of the  Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 170, "question" : "By which of the following a new State is formed? ", "answer" : " Constitutional Amendment  "},
{ "id" : 171, "question" : "The final interpreter to Indian Constitution is ", "answer" : " Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 172, "question" : "Every Amendment of Indian Constitution has to be approved by the ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 173, "question" : "Which one of the following States has a separate Constitution? ", "answer" : " Jammu & Kashmir  "},
{ "id" : 174, "question" : "Apart from the Jammu & Kashmir, which other State has been provided special protection  in certain matters? ", "answer" : " Nagaland  "},
{ "id" : 175, "question" : "Article 356 of the Constitution of India deals with ", "answer" : " Proclamation of President’s  Rule in a State  "},
{ "id" : 176, "question" : "The State of Jammu & Kashmir was accorded special status under ", "answer" : " Article 370  "},
{ "id" : 177, "question" : "The Constitution of Jammu & Kashmir was framed by ", "answer" : " A special Constituent  Assembly set up by the State  "},
{ "id" : 178, "question" : "The Constitution of Jammu & Kashmir came into force on ", "answer" : " 26.01.1957   "},
{ "id" : 179, "question" : "The special status of Jammu & Kashmir implies that the State has separate ", "answer" : "  Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 180, "question" : "In case of Jammu & Kashmir, an Amendment to the Constitution become applicable ", "answer" : "  only after the President issued the necessary orders under the Article 370  "},
{ "id" : 181, "question" : "Under the Parliamentary system of the Government, ", "answer" : " the Cabinet as a whole is  responsible to the Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 182, "question" : "Who is authorized to initiate a Bill for Constitutional Amendment? ", "answer" : " Either House of  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 183, "question" : "The power of Parliament to amend the Constitution ", "answer" : "   includes power to amend by  way of addition, variation or repeal  "},
{ "id" : 184, "question" : "Which Article empowers the Parliament to amend the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : " 368   "},
{ "id" : 185, "question" : "Ninth Schedule to the Constitution is added by way of ____ Constitutional Amendment. ", "answer" : " 1st   "},
{ "id" : 186, "question" : "What is contained in the Tenth Schedule of the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : " Provisions  regarding disqualification on grounds of defection  "},
{ "id" : 187, "question" : "Mahatma Gandhiji was first referred to as the ‘Father of the Nation’ by ", "answer" : " Subhash  Chandra Bose  "},
{ "id" : 188, "question" : "‘Jai Hind’, the nationalist slogan of India was coined by ", "answer" : " Subhash Chandra Bose   "},
{ "id" : 189, "question" : "Who framed the Constitution of India? ", "answer" : " Dr. B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 190, "question" : "Which famous leader raised the slogan, “Tell the Slave, He is a Slave and He will  Revolt”? ", "answer" : "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 191, "question" : "Who said, “Those who attack Congress and spare Nehru are fools. They do not know the  ABCs of the politics …….?” ", "answer" : "Dr. B. R. Ambedkar  "},
{ "id" : 192, "question" : "What is the name given to the Ambedkar’s house built for himself, his family and books  at Dadar, in Bombay? ", "answer" : "Rajagriha   "},
{ "id" : 193, "question" : "Indian Constitution is ", "answer" : " Wholly written  "},
{ "id" : 194, "question" : "The Indian Constitution is ", "answer" : " Lengthy, Written  "},
{ "id" : 195, "question" : "Consider the following statement: On eve of launch of Quit India Movement, Mahatma  Gandhi ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 196, "question" : "The ‘Homespun Movement’ and the Salt March promoted by Mahatma Gandhiji in India  are examples of his policy of ", "answer" : " Non-violent protest  "},
{ "id" : 197, "question" : "Which year is considered to be a memorable landmark in the history of India’s Struggle  for Freedom? ", "answer" : " 1921  "},
{ "id" : 198, "question" : "The First War of Independence took place in the year (OR) In which year did the Sepoy  Mutiny, India’s first Freedom Struggle, takes place? ", "answer" : " 1857   "},
{ "id" : 199, "question" : "Mahatma Gandhiji was the editor of ", "answer" : " Young India  "},
{ "id" : 200, "question" : "Who was not a member of the Constituent Assembly? ", "answer" : " Mahatma Gandhi  "},
{ "id" : 201, "question" : "Who among the following was not a member of the Royal Commission on the Public  Services in India, 1912?", "answer" : "Bal Gangadhar Tilak  "},
{ "id" : 202, "question" : "Which national leader of India, preached through his paper ‘Kesari’, his new ideals of  self-help and national revival among the masses?", "answer" : "Bal Gangadhar Tilak   "},
{ "id" : 203, "question" : "Which newspaper was started by Lokamanya Tilak to serve as a mouthpiece for the  Indians in the Freedom Struggle? ", "answer" : " Kesari  "},
{ "id" : 204, "question" : "The Cabinet Mission to India was headed by ", "answer" : " Lord Pethick-Lawrence  "},
{ "id" : 205, "question" : "In which one of the following provinces was a Congress ministry not formed under Act of  1935? ", "answer" : " Punjab   "},
{ "id" : 206, "question" : "Under whose Presidency was the Lahore Session of the Indian National Congress held in  the year 1929 wherein a resolution was adopted to gain complete independence from the British? - ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru   "},
{ "id" : 207, "question" : "Unity between the Congress and Muslim League (Lucknow Pact) and between the  Moderates and Extremists took place in ", "answer" : " 1916   "},
{ "id" : 208, "question" : "At which Congress Session was the Working Committee authorized to launch a  programme of Civil Disobedience? ", "answer" : " Lahore   "},
{ "id" : 209, "question" : "The historic 1929 Lahore Session of Indian National Congress was presided over by ", "answer" : "  Jawaharlal Nehru  "},
{ "id" : 210, "question" : "Who among the following drafted the resolution on Fundamental Rights for the Karachi  Session of Congress in 1931? ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru   "},
{ "id" : 211, "question" : "Who among the following was the Chairman of the Union Constitution Committee of the  Constituent Assembly? ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru  "},
{ "id" : 212, "question" : "Who made the comment on the Constitution should not be so rigid that it cannot be  adapted to the changing needs of national development and strength? ", "answer" : " Rajiv Gandhi  "},
{ "id" : 213, "question" : "‘Vande Mataram’ was first sung at the session of the Indian National Congress in ", "answer" : "  1896  "},
{ "id" : 214, "question" : "The expression ‘Tryst with Destiny’ was used by Jawaharlal Nehru on the occasion of ", "answer" : "August Declaration  "},
{ "id" : 215, "question" : "India enacted an important event of Indian National Movement celebrating the 75th  anniversary. Which was it? ", "answer" : "Civil Obedience Movement  "},
{ "id" : 216, "question" : "Which one of the following principle with regard to ‘Panchsheel’? ", "answer" : " Mutual Non- interference in each other’s internal matters, Mutual Non-aggression, Mutual respect for  each others territorial integrity and sovereignty  "},
{ "id" : 217, "question" : "The Agreement between India and China, by which both accepted ‘Panchsheel’ as the  basis of their relations, was signed in ", "answer" : " 1954   "},
{ "id" : 218, "question" : "‘Panchsheel’ was signed between ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru and Chou-En-Lai   "},
{ "id" : 219, "question" : "When was the famous Gandhi–Irwin Pact signed? ", "answer" : " 1931  "},
{ "id" : 220, "question" : "Who coined the term ‘Non-Alignment’? ", "answer" : " Krishna Menon  "},
{ "id" : 221, "question" : "Who among the following repealed the Vernacular Press Act? ", "answer" : " Lord Ripon   "},
{ "id" : 222, "question" : "Who was assigned the task of partitioning India in 1947? ", "answer" : "  Sir Cyril Redcliffe  "},
{ "id" : 223, "question" : "Which Englishman’s role was control to the founding of the Indian National Congress?   (OR) Which British was elemental in the formation of the Indian National Congress? ", "answer" : " Allen  Octavian Hume   "},
{ "id" : 224, "question" : "Subhash Chandra Bose renamed what as “Shaheed and Swaraj”? ", "answer" : "The Andaman  and Nicobar Islands  "},
{ "id" : 225, "question" : "Which party was founded by Subhash Chandra Bose in the year 1939 after he broke away  from the Congress? (OR) Which political party was founded by Subhash Chandra Bose? ", "answer" : "  Forward Bloc  "},
{ "id" : 226, "question" : "The Indian National Army was founded by ", "answer" : " Subhash Chandra Bose  "},
{ "id" : 227, "question" : "In which year and place did Subhash Chandra Bose re-organized the Azad Hind Fauz  (also known as Indian National Army–INA)? ", "answer" : " 1943, Singapore   "},
{ "id" : 228, "question" : "By what name was the woman’s regiment of the Indian National Army known? ", "answer" : " Rani  Jhansi Regiment  "},
{ "id" : 229, "question" : "The INA, organized by Subhash Chandra Bose, surrendered to the British after the  collapse of ", "answer" : " Japan  "},
{ "id" : 230, "question" : "During the Indian Freedom Struggle, who among the following proposed that Swaraj  should be defined has complete independence free from all foreign controls? ", "answer" : " Abul Kalam  Azad  "},
{ "id" : 231, "question" : "The leader of the Bardoli Satyagraha (1928) was ", "answer" : "Vallabhbhai Patel   "},
{ "id" : 232, "question" : "When did the British Parliament pass the Indian Independence Bill? ", "answer" : "01.07.1947  "},
{ "id" : 233, "question" : "The reference to Hindus in Article 25 of the Constitution does not include ", "answer" : " Parsees   "},
{ "id" : 234, "question" : "Financial allocation for education was made for the first time by the Charter Act of ", "answer" : "  1813  "},
{ "id" : 235, "question" : "‘Go Back to the Vedas’ was the motto of ", "answer" : " Swami Dayananda Saraswati  "},
{ "id" : 236, "question" : "Which of the following persons became Vice President after serving as acting President of  India for a short duration? ", "answer" : " Mohammed Hidyathullah  "},
{ "id" : 237, "question" : "In 1921, a Session of the Indian National Congress was held when its President was in  prison and with some other leader acting as its President. Who was the Congress President in  prison? ", "answer" : " C. R. Das  "},
{ "id" : 238, "question" : "Following the famous ‘Quit India Resolve’, the top Congress leaders were arrested On ", "answer" : "  09.08.1942  "},
{ "id" : 239, "question" : "The ‘Quit India Movement’ started at and when ", "answer" : " Bombay, 08.08.1942  "},
{ "id" : 240, "question" : "Which famous Movement did Mahatma Gandhi launch in August 1942? ", "answer" : " Quit India  Movement   "},
{ "id" : 241, "question" : "In how many provinces did the Indian National Congress form Governments after the  elections to the Assemblies held under the Government of India Act of 1935? ", "answer" : " 7  "},
{ "id" : 242, "question" : "The Muslim League declared its goal of forming Pakistan in which city in 1940? ", "answer" : "  Karachi  "},
{ "id" : 243, "question" : "Name the only Indian ruler who has died fighting the British? ", "answer" : " Tippu Sultan  "},
{ "id" : 244, "question" : "Who was the first Muslim Invader of India? ", "answer" : " Mohammed Bin Kasim   "},
{ "id" : 245, "question" : "The words ‘Satyameva Jayate’ inscribed in Devanagiri script below the abacus of the  State Emblem of India are taken from ", "answer" : " Mundaka Upanishad  "},
{ "id" : 246, "question" : "The design of the National Flag of India was adopted by the Constituent Assembly On ", "answer" : " 22.08.1947  "},
{ "id" : 247, "question" : "Who gave the first draft of the Constitution to the Drafting Committee to consider and  improve ", "answer" : " B. N. Rau  "},
{ "id" : 248, "question" : "The Final Draft of the Constitution was prepared by ", "answer" : " S. N. Mukherjee  "},
{ "id" : 249, "question" : "The State of Bombay, a Part A State in the original Constitution, was split into two States,  Gujarat and Maharashtra, in ", "answer" : " 1960  "},
{ "id" : 250, "question" : "The Preamble says that the State in India will assure the dignity of the individual. The  Constitution seeks to achieve this object by guaranteeing ", "answer" : "Equal FRs to each citizen  "},
{ "id" : 251, "question" : "Our Preamble mentions the _____ kinds of Justice. ", "answer" : " Social, Economic and  Political   "},
{ "id" : 252, "question" : "Articles 19(1)(f) and 31 were deleted and Article 300-A was inserted by the following  Constitution Amendment Act ", "answer" : "44th   "},
{ "id" : 253, "question" : "Which of the following Article of the Constitution cannot be amended by a simple  majority in both the Houses of Parliament? ", "answer" : " 15  "},
{ "id" : 254, "question" : "Which of the following events made Gandhiji to launch, for the first time, Civil  Disobedience Movement ", "answer" : "Promulgation of Rowlatt Act of 1919  "},
{ "id" : 255, "question" : "Where did Mahatma Gandhiji first try the weapon of ‘Satyagraha’? ", "answer" : " South Africa   "},
{ "id" : 256, "question" : "The most effective measure against injustice adopted by Gandhiji was ", "answer" : "Fasting  "},
{ "id" : 257, "question" : "Gandhiji started Satyagraha in 1919 to protest against the ", "answer" : " Rowlatt Act  "},
{ "id" : 258, "question" : "Which of the following Acts of British Parliament envisaged for the first time a close  association of Indians with the administration? ", "answer" : "Indian Councils Act, 1909  "},
{ "id" : 259, "question" : "Which of the following Acts gave representation to the Indians for the first time in  legislation? ", "answer" : " Indian Councils Act, 1909   "},
{ "id" : 260, "question" : "Which leader dominated the Lucknow Pact in December, 1916?", "answer" : "Bal Gangadhar  Tilak   "},
{ "id" : 261, "question" : "The famous Lucknow Pact between the Congress and the Muslim League was concluded  in ", "answer" : " 1916  "},
{ "id" : 262, "question" : "Which present day country was a part of British India from 1886–1937? ", "answer" : " Myanmar  "},
{ "id" : 263, "question" : "Which one of the following is related to the development of education in Modern India? ", "answer" : " Resolution of 1835, Regulating Act, Charter Act, 1813  "},
{ "id" : 264, "question" : "Which British Official was sent to Lahore to negotiate the Treaty of Amritsar with Ranjit  Singh? ", "answer" : "  Charles T. Metcalfe  "},
{ "id" : 265, "question" : "Who was the Governor General of India during the Sepoy Mutiny? ", "answer" : " Lord Canning  "},
{ "id" : 266, "question" : "Who was the first woman President of UN General Assembly? ", "answer" : "Vijayalakshmi  Pandit  "},
{ "id" : 267, "question" : "Which Section of the Limitation Act defines Tort? ", "answer" : "Section 2 (m)   "},
{ "id" : 268, "question" : "The seeds of the doctrine of Basic Structure can be traced to the following: ", "answer" : "The  majority judgment of Chief Justice Subba Rao in Golak Nath V/s State of Punjab  "},
{ "id" : 269, "question" : "The purpose of the Ilbert Bill was ", "answer" : " To remove an anomaly in the Criminal  Procedure Code of 1873, according to which no magistrate or sessions judge could try a  European or British subject unless he was himself of European birth  "},
{ "id" : 270, "question" : "In India, the liability of the State for wrongs committed by its servants – ", "answer" : " Is the same  as what that of the East India Company prior to the year 1858 (According to Case Kasturi  Lal Raliaram Jain V/s State of Uttar Pradesh)  "},
{ "id" : 271, "question" : "An Amendment of the Constitution of India for the purpose of creating a new State in  India must be passed by ", "answer" : " A simple majority in the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 272, "question" : "On which of the following did the Mahalonobis Model laid greater emphasis for planned  development in India after Independence? ", "answer" : " Heavy Industries Development   "},
{ "id" : 273, "question" : "How our Constitution was criticized? ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 274, "question" : "What has been described as the ‘Indian Political Horoscope’?", "answer" : "Preamble   "},
{ "id" : 275, "question" : "Who called the word for Preamble as ‘Political Horoscope of India’? ", "answer" : " K.M. Munshi  "},
{ "id" : 276, "question" : "What is meant by saying that India is a ‘Secular State’? ", "answer" : " Complete detachment from  the affairs of the religion  "},
{ "id" : 277, "question" : "Where in the Indian Constitution, ‘Economic Justice’ has been provided as one of the  objectives? ", "answer" : "Preamble and DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 278, "question" : "Who treated as ‘Sovereign’ in Constitution of India? ", "answer" : " People  "},
{ "id" : 279, "question" : "Home Rule League was founded by ", "answer" : " Annie Beasant  "},
{ "id" : 280, "question" : "Who set up the first school of untouchables in India? ", "answer" : " Jyothiba Phule, 1948, Pune   "},
{ "id" : 281, "question" : "In which year was Untouchability abolished in India? ", "answer" : "1950  "},
{ "id" : 282, "question" : "Shimla Agreement between India and Pakistan was signed during ", "answer" : " 1972   "},
{ "id" : 283, "question" : "The first visible effect of Constitution was ", "answer" : " Disappearance of Princely States  "},
{ "id" : 284, "question" : "The Constitution of India provides _______ system of Government. ", "answer" : "Cabinet  "},
{ "id" : 285, "question" : "Kashmiri is the Official Language of ", "answer" : " No State in the Indian Union   "},
{ "id" : 286, "question" : "In which year were the Indian States reorganized on a linguistic basis? ", "answer" : "1956  "},
{ "id" : 287, "question" : "The Lal in Lal, Bal, Pal was ", "answer" : " Lala Lajpat Rai   "},
{ "id" : 288, "question" : "Indian Constitution is called ‘Quasi-Federal’ because it has ", "answer" : " Single Judiciary  "},
{ "id" : 289, "question" : "Who succeeded Lord Mountbatten as the first Indian Governor General of the Indian  dominion till 26th January 1950 when India became a Republic? ", "answer" : "C. Rajagopalachari                 II. FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS (FRs)  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "India is referred as ___ under the Indian Constitution.", "answer" : " Bharat   "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "Who is empowered to admit a new State to the Union of India? ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "Which important Human Right is protected in Article 21 of our Constitution? ", "answer" : " Right to  Life and Liberty  "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "The Constitution confers a special authority for the enforcement of FRs on the ", "answer" : " Supreme  Court  "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "The FRs of the Indian Citizen in our Constitution are contained in (OR) FRs are guaranteed  under ____ of the Indian Constitution. ", "answer" : " Part III  "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "Under Article 368, Parliament has no power to repeal FRs because they are ", "answer" : " Basic  Structure of Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "FRs can be claimed against the ", "answer" : " State  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "The FRs, which cannot be suspended even during the emergency, are Articles _____. ", "answer" : " 20 and 21  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "Clause (1) of Article 13 is applicable only to ", "answer" : " Pre-constitutional Laws "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "Original Constitution classified FRs into seven categories but now there are ", "answer" : " Six "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "India’s desire for civil liberties started from the struggle for independence against the ", "answer" : " British Rule  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "India borrowed the idea of incorporating FRs in the Constitution from ", "answer" : " USA "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "The concept of Single Citizenship is borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " Britain "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "The concept of Dual Citizenship in the Union of India was recommended by ", "answer" : " L. M. Singhvi Committee.  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution, Citizenship of a person can be determined at the commencement of the Constitution? ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "Which Article describes the persons voluntarily acquiring Citizenship of a foreign State not to be an Indian Citizen? ", "answer" : " 9  "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "Who is authorized to lay down qualifications to acquire the Citizenship? ", "answer" : " President "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "Which of the following is a qualification to acquire Citizenship by Naturalization? ", "answer" : " A person is in service of Government of India from 12 months  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "FRs are not applicable to", "answer" : "Armed Forces "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution empowers the Parliament to enact the provisions for acquisition and termination of Citizenship? ", "answer" : " 11  "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "By which FR other FRs is protected? ", "answer" : "Right to Constitutional Remedies "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "Right to Property is a legal right under the Article ____. ", "answer" : " 300A "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "Which of the following is not a FR? [Right to] ", "answer" : "Property "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "Which of the following has ceased to be a FR in the Indian Constitution? [Right to] ", "answer" : " Property  "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "Which among the following is not a FR? [Right to] ", "answer" : " Strike "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Which FR has been a subject of maximum controversy and litigation? [Right to] ", "answer" : " Property  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "The Right to private property was dropped from the list of FRs by the (OR) Right to property took the shape of legal right by way of ", "answer" : " 44th Amendment  "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "The Right to equality guaranteed by the Indian Constitution does not include ", "answer" : " Economic Equality  "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "‘Equality before the Law’ implies ", "answer" : " absence of any privilege in favor of any person "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "Which Resolution for the first time expressed the concept of equality before the law? ", "answer" : " Swaraj Bill  "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "The FRs of the Indian Citizen were ", "answer" : " Enshrined in Original Constitution "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Which one of the FRs was described by Dr. B. R. Ambedkar as the ‘Heart and Soul of the Constitution’? [Right to] ", "answer" : " Constitutional Remedies  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "Which of the following confers upon the citizens the right to approach a court of law for the  protection and restoration of FRs? (Right) ", "answer" : " Constitutional Remedies  "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "The Right to Constitutional Remedies are ", "answer" : " Fundamental Rights   "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "The Constitutional remedies under the Article 32 can be suspended by the ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Writs can be issued for the enforcement of FRs by the ", "answer" : " Supreme Court   "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "Which one of the following FRs is restrained by the Preventive Detention Act? [Right to] ", "answer" : " - Freedom  "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "Who enjoys the right to impose reasonable restrictions on the FRs of Indian citizen? (OR)  Who has the power to empower the Courts other than the Supreme and High Courts to issue writs  and order for the forcement of the FRs? ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "Who can abridge any FR without damaging or destroying the basic features of the  Constitution? ", "answer" : "Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "Which one of the following Courts is responsible for the enforcement of FRs? ", "answer" : " Supreme  Court  "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "Which of the following is the guardian of the FRs of the citizens? (OR) Who is the  Protector and Guarantor of the FRs? ", "answer" : " Supreme Court   "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "Any violation of FRs can be presented to ", "answer" : " Both Supreme and High Courts  "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "Who is authorized to impose restrictions on FRs?", "answer" : "Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "The FRs of the Indian citizen ", "answer" : " can be suspended by the President during national  emergency  "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "FRs are ", "answer" : " Those basic conditions of social life without which a Citizen cannot be at  his/her best self  "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "The FRs ensure the protection of ", "answer" : " Citizens against arbitrary rule  "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "Our Constitution grants to the citizens ______ FRs. ", "answer" : " Six   "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "‘Ultra vires’ means ", "answer" : " Without authority  "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "Who are not entitled to form Union? ", "answer" : " Police   "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "By the Citizenship Act of 1955, when he / she will be loosing the Citizenship? ", "answer" : "  Renunciation, Deprivation &  Termination   "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "Who quoted ‘Child of today is the Citizen of tomorrow’? ", "answer" : " Jawaharlal Nehru   "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "Generally, the census is conducted for _____ year(s). ", "answer" : " 10   "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "Who quoted ‘Freedom is my Birth Right’? ", "answer" : " Sardar   "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "What is the age in years for casting their vote? ", "answer" : " 18  "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "Which Article and Amendment changes the right to vote from 21 to 18 years? ", "answer" : " 326 and  61st   "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "‘Creamy Layer’ means ", "answer" : " Persons having higher incomes   "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "‘Backward Class (BC)’ can be classified into ", "answer" : " Most Backward Class   "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "Mandal Commission deals with ", "answer" : " Reservation for backward class people   "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "This is one of the grounds for classification ", "answer" : " Annual income   "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "‘Equal Protection of Law’ meanst ", "answer" : " he same law shall apply to all who are similarly  situated  "},
{ "id" : 61, "question" : "Seats in Educational Institutions can be reserved for ", "answer" : " Socially and Educationally  backward class people  "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "Minimum percentage of reservation in a educational institution is ", "answer" : " 50%   "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "Minority may be ", "answer" : " linguistic or religious  "},
{ "id" : 64, "question" : "This is not the ground to impose restriction on Right of freedom of speech and expression - ", "answer" : " Public nuisance   "},
{ "id" : 65, "question" : "Which one of the following courts is responsible for the enforcement of FRs? ", "answer" : " Supreme  Court  "},
{ "id" : 66, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is correct? ", "answer" : " FRs are superior to the DPSP  "},
{ "id" : 67, "question" : "In which case did the Supreme Court restrict the authority of Parliament to amend FRs and  declared these rights to be absolute, permanent and unalterable? ", "answer" : " Golak Nath Case   "},
{ "id" : 68, "question" : "In the famous Keshavananda Bharti V/s State of Kerala Case, the Supreme Court asserts  the power of the parliament to amend the Constitution under Article 368 subject to ", "answer" : " Certain  implied and inherent limitation of not amending the Basic Structure of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 69, "question" : "‘Rule of Law which permeates the entire fabric of the Indian Constitution excludes  arbitrariness’. This principle is laid down in ", "answer" : " Maneka Gandhi V/s Union Government Case  "},
{ "id" : 70, "question" : "The protection guaranteed under Article 21 is available even to convicts in jails. The  convicts are not by mere reasons of their conviction deprived of the entire FRs which they  otherwise possess. This is the principle laid down in ", "answer" : " Sunil Batra V/s Delhi Administration  Case  "},
{ "id" : 71, "question" : "Gender Equality includes protection from sexual harassment and right to work with dignity,  which is universally recognized as basic Human Right. This principle is laid down in ", "answer" : " Vishaka  V/s State of Rajasthan Case  "},
{ "id" : 72, "question" : "The Supreme Court held that the nuisance caused by the pollution of the river Ganga is a  public nuisance which is wide spread and affecting the lives of large number of persons and  therefore any particular person can take proceedings to stop it. This PIL is ", "answer" : " M.C. Mehta V/s  Union of India (1988)  "},
{ "id" : 73, "question" : "Charging capitation fees for admission to educational institutions is illegal and amounted to  denial of citizen’s right to education. This principle is laid down in ", "answer" : " Mohin Jain V/s State of  Karnataka Case   "},
{ "id" : 74, "question" : "The right to establish an educational institution and imparting education is not a  commercial activity. This principle is laid down in ", "answer" : " Unnikrishnan V/s State of Andhra  Pradesh Case  "},
{ "id" : 75, "question" : "The principle of Judicial review of President’s Rule in State under the Article 356 is laid  down in ", "answer" : "  S.R. Bommai V/s Union of India  "},
{ "id" : 76, "question" : "Who among the following has voting rights? ", "answer" : " An adult resident citizen of a State  "},
{ "id" : 77, "question" : "The right to strike is", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 78, "question" : "Which one is not a FR? ", "answer" : " The Right to Strike   "},
{ "id" : 79, "question" : "Which one of the following FRs has been subject of maximum litigation since the  inauguration of the Constitution? (Right to) ", "answer" : " Property   "},
{ "id" : 80, "question" : "The rule of Equality before law is not applicable to ", "answer" : " Governor of State  "},
{ "id" : 81, "question" : "Right to Equality is guaranteed under the Article ____. ", "answer" : " 14  "},
{ "id" : 82, "question" : "Article 14 guarantees equality before the law to ", "answer" : " All persons  "},
{ "id" : 83, "question" : "‘Right to Equality’ means ", "answer" : " permits the State to make special provisions for women,  children and backward classes  "},
{ "id" : 84, "question" : "Equal opportunity in matters of public employment is guaranteed under the Article ", "answer" : " 16  "},
{ "id" : 85, "question" : "Which among the following FRs abolishes discrimination? ", "answer" : " Equality  "},
{ "id" : 86, "question" : "Untouchability is associated with _______ inequality. ", "answer" : " Social   "},
{ "id" : 87, "question" : "‘Right to Freedom’ can be restricted in the interest of ", "answer" : " Public order, Security of the  State & Friendly relations with foreign States   "},
{ "id" : 88, "question" : "This is not the ground to impose restriction on the right of freedom of speech and  expression. ", "answer" : " Law and order  "},
{ "id" : 89, "question" : "Which one of the following right conferred by the Constitution is also available to non- citizens? ", "answer" : " Right to constitutional remedies  "},
{ "id" : 90, "question" : "The Sikhs in India are permitted to carry Kirpans. Under which FR are they permitted to do  so? ", "answer" : "  Right to freedom of religion  "},
{ "id" : 91, "question" : "Freedom of Speech under the Indian Constitution is subject to reasonable restrictions on the  grounds of protection of ", "answer" : " Sovereignty and integrity of the country  "},
{ "id" : 92, "question" : "Which one of the following is considered as Bulwark of Democracy? (Right to) ", "answer" : "  Speech   "},
{ "id" : 93, "question" : "One of the restrictions of freedom of speech and expression is ", "answer" : " Contempt of Court   "},
{ "id" : 94, "question" : "At present, the Right to property is a ", "answer" : " Human Right  "},
{ "id" : 95, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a FR? (Right to) ", "answer" : " Property  "},
{ "id" : 96, "question" : "The main objective of the cultural and educational rights granted to the citizens is to ", "answer" : "  Help the minorities to conserve their culture  "},
{ "id" : 97, "question" : "A person can move to Supreme Court directly in vent of violation of FRs under Article", "answer" : "  32  "},
{ "id" : 98, "question" : "A citizen’s FRs are protected ", "answer" : " when the citizen approaches the court for remedy  "},
{ "id" : 99, "question" : "The FRs of a citizen can be suspended by the ", "answer" : " President during a National Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 100, "question" : "For the enforcement of the FRs, the courts can issue ", "answer" : " A Writ  "},
{ "id" : 101, "question" : "Which FR granted by the Constitution prohibits traffic in human beings? ", "answer" : " Right  against exploitation  "},
{ "id" : 102, "question" : "‘Traffic in Human beings’ means ", "answer" : " selling or purchasing men and women  "},
{ "id" : 103, "question" : "Right against exploitation prohibits ", "answer" : " Traffic in Human being  "},
{ "id" : 104, "question" : "Right to practice and propagate any religion is the subject to ", "answer" : " public order  "},
{ "id" : 105, "question" : "Right to property was eliminated form the list of FRs during the tenure of ", "answer" : " Morarji  Desai   "},
{ "id" : 106, "question" : "Legal equality under the Indian Constitution implies that ", "answer" : " there should be equality  amongst equals and inequality among unequals  "},
{ "id" : 107, "question" : "Who of the following can amend the FRs granted by the Constitution? ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 108, "question" : "A citizen can directly move the Supreme Court for any violation of FR under the Article  ____. ", "answer" : "34  "},
{ "id" : 109, "question" : "The main objective of the FRs is to ", "answer" : " ensure individual liberty  "},
{ "id" : 110, "question" : "Under the Indian Constitution, a citizen ", "answer" : " can be deprived of life and liberty only in  accordance with the procedure established by the law  "},
{ "id" : 111, "question" : "Constitution grants Right against exploitation to “Children / Women / Tribals / Dalits” ", "answer" : "  C and W   "},
{ "id" : 112, "question" : "Which of the Provision authorizes Parliament to discriminate in favor of women against  men? ", "answer" : "Article 15 (3)  "},
{ "id" : 113, "question" : "Article 15 (3) confers a special provisions to ", "answer" : "Women and Children   "},
{ "id" : 114, "question" : "Article 15 (4) confers a special provisions for the advancement of ", "answer" : " SCs and STs  "},
{ "id" : 115, "question" : "The prohibition imposed by the Article 20 is applicable to ", "answer" : "Criminal cases  "},
{ "id" : 116, "question" : "The principle “No person shall be prosecuted and punished for same offence more than  once” is ", "answer" : "Double jeopardy  "},
{ "id" : 117, "question" : "If an Act is not an offence on the date of its commission, a law enacted in future cannot  make it so, is the principle of ", "answer" : " Ex-post facto law  "},
{ "id" : 118, "question" : "‘Ex-post facto law’ means ", "answer" : "  passing criminal law with retrospective effect  "},
{ "id" : 119, "question" : "An arrested person should be allowed ", "answer" : " to consult his Lawyer  "},
{ "id" : 120, "question" : "Every person who has been arrested has the right to be produced before the ", "answer" : " Magistrate  "},
{ "id" : 121, "question" : "A person arrested has to be produced before the Magistrate within ", "answer" : " 24 hours   "},
{ "id" : 122, "question" : "The right of the accused to be informed about his ground of arrest is ", "answer" : " Mandatory  "},
{ "id" : 123, "question" : "No person who is arrested shall be detained in custody without being informed ", "answer" : " On the  grounds for such arrest  "},
{ "id" : 124, "question" : "The provisions enshrined under the Article 22 are ", "answer" : " Mandatory  "},
{ "id" : 125, "question" : "Article 21A was inserted under our Constitution by way of ____ Constitutional  Amendment. ", "answer" : "  86th   "},
{ "id" : 126, "question" : "Earlier to 86th Amendment, Article 21A is in the form of ", "answer" : " DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 127, "question" : "What is the object of Article 21A of the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Primary Education   "},
{ "id" : 128, "question" : "Right to education guaranteed under the Article 21A shall be between the age group of ", "answer" : "  6 to 14  "},
{ "id" : 129, "question" : "Right to Primary Education guaranteed under the Article 21A was inserted into the  Constitution by _____ Constitutional Amendment. ", "answer" : " 86th   "},
{ "id" : 130, "question" : "Which of the following has been included in the list of FRs to Indian citizen? ", "answer" : "  Education to all children between 6-14 years of age  "},
{ "id" : 131, "question" : "Right to Education is a part of ", "answer" : " Right to life  "},
{ "id" : 132, "question" : "Right to Life includes Right to ", "answer" : " get education  "},
{ "id" : 133, "question" : "Education has became the joint responsibility of the Center and State Governments  through a Constitutional Amendment in ", "answer" : " 1976  "},
{ "id" : 134, "question" : "The Constitution does not protect the Right of the minority with regard to ", "answer" : " Cult  "},
{ "id" : 135, "question" : "Which among the following Article guarantees the Right of minorities to establish and  administer the educational institutions? ", "answer" : " 30  "},
{ "id" : 136, "question" : "The Right to establish educational institutional under Article 30 is applicable to ", "answer" : "  Linguistic Minority  "},
{ "id" : 137, "question" : "Right to Decent environment includes ", "answer" : " Right to life  "},
{ "id" : 138, "question" : "A person is detained under Preventive Detention Law when ", "answer" : " he is likely to cause harm  to the public  "},
{ "id" : 139, "question" : "The forced labour does not include service rendered under ", "answer" : " compulsion of economic  circumstances  "},
{ "id" : 140, "question" : "This is one of the basis for classification ", "answer" : " geographical  "},
{ "id" : 141, "question" : "Sexual harassment of working women is violation of ", "answer" : "  FRs  "},
{ "id" : 142, "question" : "The popular name for a nine-Judge Bench of the Supreme Court has in ‘Indra Sawhney  V/s Union of India Case’ is ", "answer" : "  Mandal Commission Case  "},
{ "id" : 143, "question" : "The Freedom of speech and expression does not include ", "answer" : " calling for ‘Bundh’  "},
{ "id" : 144, "question" : "Freedom of press is included in Right to ", "answer" : " freedom of speech and expression  "},
{ "id" : 145, "question" : "Freedom of press is protected under the Article ", "answer" : " 19(1)(d)   "},
{ "id" : 146, "question" : "‘Right to Privacy’ includes Right to ", "answer" : " personal liberty  "},
{ "id" : 147, "question" : "A citizen of India may be debarred from the Right to vote on the ground of ", "answer" : "  unsoundness of mind, crime or corrupt or illegal practice & non-resident  "},
{ "id" : 148, "question" : "Freedoms guaranteed under the Article 19 are suspended during emergency on the ground  of ", "answer" : " War or external aggression  "},
{ "id" : 149, "question" : "Right to Freedom guaranteed under Article 19 ____ during emergency. ", "answer" : "  can be  suspended   "},
{ "id" : 150, "question" : "Article 19(2) under the Indian Constitution speaks about ", "answer" : " Reasonable restrictions   "},
{ "id" : 151, "question" : "India has recognized ", "answer" : " No religion as National Religion  "},
{ "id" : 152, "question" : "Freedom of religion guaranteed under the Article 25 is applicable to ", "answer" : "  Citizens only,  Persons residing within India & Persons of Indian Origin  "},
{ "id" : 153, "question" : "The secular provisions under the Indian Constitution are guaranteed under Article____. ", "answer" : " - 22  "},
{ "id" : 154, "question" : "Article 25 guarantees freedom of religion, but it is subject to ", "answer" : " Public order, Morality  & Health  "},
{ "id" : 155, "question" : "‘Contempt of Court’ places restriction on which of the following FR? (Right) ", "answer" : "  Freedom  "},
{ "id" : 156, "question" : "Right to life and personal liberty guaranteed under Article 21 implies ", "answer" : "  right of every  human being to live with dignity  "},
{ "id" : 157, "question" : "Any law depriving personal liberty guaranteed under the Article 21 had to confirm with ", "answer" : " - Article 20 &  Article 22   "},
{ "id" : 158, "question" : "Any law laid down by the Parliament to deprive the personal liberty should be ", "answer" : " Fair,  Reasonable &  Just   "},
{ "id" : 159, "question" : "This is not a Writ. ", "answer" : "  Writ of Prevention   "},
{ "id" : 160, "question" : "How many types of writs are there? ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 161, "question" : "Writ can be directly filed in the ", "answer" : " Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 162, "question" : "The writ of Habeas Corpus is issued ", "answer" : " in the form of an order calling upon a person  who has detained another person to bring that person before court and show authority for  such detention  "},
{ "id" : 163, "question" : "The writ of Quo Warranto is an order from a superior court ", "answer" : " whereby it can call upon  a person to show under what authority he is holding the office  "},
{ "id" : 164, "question" : "The writ of Mandamus is issued by a superior court to ", "answer" : "  to command a person or  public authority to do something in the nature of the public duty  "},
{ "id" : 165, "question" : "The writ of Certiorari is issued by a superior court ", "answer" : "  to an inferior court to transfer  the record of proceedings in a case for review  "},
{ "id" : 166, "question" : "The writ of Prohibition is issued by a superior court ", "answer" : " to prevent an inferior court or  tribunal from exceeding its jurisdiction or acting contrary to the rules of natural justice  "},
{ "id" : 167, "question" : "Writ of Prohibition ", "answer" : " Prohibits lower court exceeding its jurisdiction  "},
{ "id" : 168, "question" : "The writ issued by the superior court directing any constitutional, statutory or nonstatutory  agency from not continuing their proceedings is known as ", "answer" : " Prohibition  "},
{ "id" : 169, "question" : "Writ of Certiorari is issued when a ", "answer" : "  judicial authority acts in excess of jurisdiction  "},
{ "id" : 170, "question" : "The writ in the form of order which removes a suit from an inferior court to superior court  to prevent an excess of jurisdiction is known as ", "answer" : " Certiorari  "},
{ "id" : 171, "question" : "Exploitation of any sort is prohibited under the Article ", "answer" : " 23  "},
{ "id" : 172, "question" : "A laborer is entitled to get at least minimum wages, otherwise ____ Article is violated.", "answer" : "  23  "},
{ "id" : 173, "question" : "Child labor is prohibited under the Article ", "answer" : " 24   "},
{ "id" : 174, "question" : "Conflict of interest may be ", "answer" : " potential  "},
{ "id" : 175, "question" : "A person is detained under the Special Law when ", "answer" : " there is likelihood of committing  offence against public  "},
{ "id" : 176, "question" : "When a person is detained under a Special Law ", "answer" : "  An Advisory Board must be  constituted within three months  "},
{ "id" : 177, "question" : "Writ of Mandamus can be issued on the ground of ", "answer" : " Non-performance of public  duties  "},
{ "id" : 178, "question" : "Writ of Quo Warranto can be issued on the ground of ", "answer" : " Unlawful occupation of public  office   "},
{ "id" : 179, "question" : "Which of the following writ is issued by the Supreme Court if it sends an order to restrain  a person from acting in an office to which he / she is not entitled? ", "answer" : "  Quo Warranto  "},
{ "id" : 180, "question" : "Writ of Habeas Corpus means ", "answer" : " produce the body before the court   "},
{ "id" : 181, "question" : "Which one of the following is a bulwark of personal freedom? ", "answer" : " Habeas Corpus  "},
{ "id" : 182, "question" : "Which one of the following writs literally means ‘you may have the body’? ", "answer" : "  Habeas  Corpus  "},
{ "id" : 183, "question" : "According to the Constitution guarantees FRs to ", "answer" : " All citizens of India  "},
{ "id" : 184, "question" : "Right to Property was excluded form the FRs during the tenure of the Government headed  by ", "answer" : "  Morarji Desai  "},
{ "id" : 185, "question" : "The Right to Property was removed from the list of FRs enlisted in the Constitution of  India through which one of the following Amendments? ", "answer" : "  44th  "},
{ "id" : 186, "question" : "The 44th Amendment of Constitution of India withdrew the FR is to ", "answer" : " Property  "},
{ "id" : 187, "question" : "The Writs for the enforcement of FRs are issued by the ", "answer" : " Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 188, "question" : "A Preventive Detention Act restraints the Right to ", "answer" : " Freedom of Movement   "},
{ "id" : 189, "question" : "Article 19 of our Constitution forms the core of the Chapter on FRs. The number of  categories of Freedoms that an Indian citizen shall have is ", "answer" : " 6  "},
{ "id" : 190, "question" : "What is the minimum permissible age in years of employment in any factory or mine? ", "answer" : "  14  "},
{ "id" : 191, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution of India says, “No child below the age of 14 years shall  be employed to work in any factory or mine or engaged in any other hazardous employment?” ", "answer" : "  24  "},
{ "id" : 192, "question" : "“Equality and arbitrariness are sworn enemies”. This was said in the following Case: ", "answer" : "  Royappa V/s Tamil Nadu State   "},
{ "id" : 193, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India has held that sexual harassment of working women amounts  to violation of rights of gender equality and right to life and personal liberty. The Case in which  the Apex Court held this was ", "answer" : "  Vishaka and Others V/s State of Rajasthan  "},
{ "id" : 194, "question" : "Consider the following statements:", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 195, "question" : "Which one is a newly added FR? (Right to) ", "answer" : "  Education of Children  "},
{ "id" : 196, "question" : "FRs can be suspended during ", "answer" : " Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 197, "question" : "Which one of the following pairs is correctly matched? ", "answer" : "  Writ of Mandamus – Issued  to the public servants  "},
{ "id" : 198, "question" : "A Writ issued by the Supreme Court compelling a quasi-judicial / public authority to  perform its mandatory duty is ", "answer" : " Mandamus   "},
{ "id" : 199, "question" : "Writs are ", "answer" : " Orders issued by courts to enforce obedience to laws  "},
{ "id" : 200, "question" : "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? ", "answer" : " Freedom of Conscience –  Include the Right to worship at the temple at all hours of the day  "},
{ "id" : 201, "question" : "The FRs are ", "answer" : " Limitation upon the State power  "},
{ "id" : 202, "question" : "FRs are ", "answer" : " Positive and Negative  "},
{ "id" : 203, "question" : "The FRs provided to the citizens are ", "answer" : " Subject to reasonable restrictions  "},
{ "id" : 204, "question" : "Which important Human Right is protected in the Article 21 of Constitution of India?  (Right to) ", "answer" : " Life and Liberty  "},
{ "id" : 205, "question" : "Freedom from arbitrary arrest is provided under ", "answer" : " Right to Personal Liberty   "},
{ "id" : 206, "question" : "The number of Fundamental Freedoms are guaranteed by our Constitution are ", "answer" : " Six  "},
{ "id" : 207, "question" : "To prevent persons coming to India from Bangladesh, Sri Lanka and African countries to  become Indian citizens a Citizenship (Amendment) Act was passed in the year ", "answer" : " 1986                       III. DIRECTIVE PRINCIPLES OF STATE POLICY (DPSP)  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "The framers of our Constitution borrowed the concept of DPSP from the Constitution of  (OR) The idea of DPSP is borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " Ireland  "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "DPSP are contained in (OR) Welfare provisions under Indian Constitution are guaranteed  under ", "answer" : "Part IV   "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "Who described the DPSP as the ‘Novel Feature of the Indian Constitution’? ", "answer" : " Ambedkar   "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "The DPSP aim at ", "answer" : "  providing a social and economic base for a genuine democracy in  the country  "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "DPSP are ", "answer" : "  positive instructions to government to work for the attainment of set  objectives  "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "DPSP are in the nature of ", "answer" : " Guidelines to State   "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "The Constitution assures economic justice to the Indian citizens through ", "answer" : " DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "The DPSP are included in our Constitution from Articles ", "answer" : "  36 to 51   "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "All of the following Articles deals with DPSP except ", "answer" : " 50  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "The DPSP are ", "answer" : " Social Rights  "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "The DPSP are ", "answer" : " Non-justiceable  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "By whom the DPSP be amended? ", "answer" : " Parliament, supported by more than 50% of  States  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "Planning in India derives its objectives from the ", "answer" : " DPSP  "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "The aim of the DPSP is to establish ", "answer" : " Welfare State in the country   "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "The enforcement of the DPSP depends on ", "answer" : "  Resources available with the Government  "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "The DPSP may be classified into ", "answer" : " Socialist, Gandhians and Liberals  "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "This Act was not passed to implement DPSP ", "answer" : " Arms Act  "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "Which one of the following is a DPSP? ", "answer" : " Raising the standards of living of the people  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "Under which Article has the State been directed to secure for the citizens a Uniform Civil  Code throughout the territory of India? ", "answer" : " 44  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "‘Common (Uniform) Civil Code’ means ", "answer" : " Common Civil law applicable to all  "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "‘Uniform Civil Code’ means ", "answer" : " A codified law applicable to all persons of India  irrespective of their religion  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "Which among the following DPSP that has not been implemented so far ", "answer" : " Uniform Civil  Code  "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "Article 51 mandates India’s Foreign Policy to ", "answer" : " Promote International Peace and  Security, Encourage settlement of international disputes by arbitration &  Maintain just and  good relations between nations  "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "The phrase ‘Economic Justice’ is found in ", "answer" : " Preamble and FRs  "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "The Right to adequate means of livelihood is to be provided by the State under the Article - ", "answer" : " 39   "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Article 45 mandates the State to provide for ", "answer" : " early childhood care and education for  all children until they complete the age of 6 years  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "It is the obligation of the State to protect every monument or place or object of artistic or  historic interest and of national importance under the Article ", "answer" : " 49  "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "The DPSP seek ", "answer" : "  To make the Constitution an instrument of social change  "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "In which part of the Constitution does the concept of welfare finds elaboration? ", "answer" : "  DPSP  "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "If India has to provide socio-economic welfare to its citizens, it should give enforceability  to ", "answer" : " DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "Certain socio-economic provisions are guaranteed under the ", "answer" : " DPSP  "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "The State imposing tax on capital and wealth according to taxation laws is protected under  Article ", "answer" : " 39  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "According to the interpretation of the Supreme Court, the word ‘Material Resources’ means  ", "answer" : "  Both Movable and Immovable property   "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "“Distribution of material resources of the community as to sub-serve the common good”  guaranteed under the Article 39B aim at the principle of _____ State. ", "answer" : "  Secular  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "Who said in the Constituent Assembly that the DPSP are like a ‘Cheque on a bank payable  at the convenience of the bank’? ", "answer" : "  K. T. Shah   "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Which one of the following wanted the DPSP to be the basis for all future legislation? ", "answer" : "   B. R. Ambedkar   "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "Which Amendment of the Constitution accorded precedence to all the DPSP over FRs? ", "answer" : "  42nd   "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "Which among the following articles guides the State to promote the welfare of the State? ", "answer" : "  38  "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "Which Article provides for the separation of Judiciary from the Executive? ", "answer" : " 50   "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "Which Article recognizes International Law under the Constitution? ", "answer" : " 51   "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "In which case did the Supreme Court strike down the Provisions of the Constitution that  accorded primacy to DPSP over FRs? ", "answer" : "  Minerva Mills   "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "Which part of the Constitution aims at establishing a Welfare State in the country? ", "answer" : "  DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "Under DPSP, the State is expected to provide free and compulsory education to all children  up to the age (in years) of ", "answer" : " 14  "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "Just and humane conditions of work and maximum living wages for workers is provided  respectively under the Articles ", "answer" : "  42 and 43   "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "The State is obligated to protect and improve the environment and safeguarding of forest  and wildlife of the country under the Article ", "answer" : " 48A   "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "Protection and Improvement of environment and safeguarding of forest and wildlife under  Article 48A is inserted into the Constitution by the ______ Amendment. ", "answer" : " 42nd   "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "Which one of the following is a DPSP? ", "answer" : " The State shall endeavor to protect and  improve the environment  "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "The 42nd Amendment made additions to DPSP with regard to the following three matters. - ", "answer" : "Participation of workers in the management of industry, Protection of the environment &   Free legal aid to the poor  "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "Consider the following statements regarding the DPSP. ", "answer" : "  The DPSP aim at realizing  the ideals of justice, liberty, equality and fraternity enshrined in the Preamble to the  Constitution &  The DPSP have to be kept in mind by the government while formulating  policies and framing laws  "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "Which one of the following DPSP is based on Gandhian Ideology? ", "answer" : "  Organization of  Village Panchayats,  Prohibition on the use of intoxicating drinks except for medicinal  purposes & To work for the development of weaker or backward sections of the society  "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "Which amendment of the Constitution sought to enhance the importance of the DPSP by  providing that no law passed to give effect to DPSP contained in Articles 39 (b) and (c) shall be  deemed to be void on the ground that it abridges the rights conferred by the Articles 14 and 19? ", "answer" : " - 25th  "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "Which of the following factors has been responsible for the slow implementation of the  DPSP?   ", "answer" : "  Vastness of the country, Lack of resources with the government & Lack of  political will  "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "Which characteristic of the DPSP provided in the Indian Constitution is incorrect? ", "answer" : "  No  law can be passed by legislature which is not in conformity with these principles  "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "Which one of the following DPSP reflects Socialist Ideology? ", "answer" : " to ensure a decent  standard of living and leisure for all workers,  to provide adequate means of livelihood to all  &  to prevent concentration of wealth and means of production and to ensure equitable  distribution of wealth and material resources  "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "The DPSP to be followed by the State for securing economic justice doe not include ", "answer" : " to  secure Uniform Civil Code  "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "Which one of the following has been wrongly listed as a DPSP based on liberal principles?  ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "The DPSP ", "answer" : " cannot be enforced in any court  "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "This is not one of the DPSP ", "answer" : "  take stringent measures to eliminate corruption  "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "This is not a DPSP. ", "answer" : " Secure just and efficient judiciary   "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "Free legal aid (Article 39A) is inserted under Indian Constitution by way of ____  Amendment. ", "answer" : " 42nd   "},
{ "id" : 61, "question" : "Village Panchayats (Article 40) are the best examples for India’s __form of government. ", "answer" : "  Democratic  "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "The Indian Constitution is silent as to which of the following DPSP? ", "answer" : " Adult Education  "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "Which one of following reasons has been wrongly listed for the slow implementation of  DPSP? ", "answer" : " opposition from the society  "},
{ "id" : 64, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a DPSP? ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 65, "question" : "Which one of the following DPSP did not form part of the original Constitution and was  added subsequently through constitutional amendments? ", "answer" : " to minimize inequality in income,  status, facilities and opportunities amongst individuals and groups,  right of the workers to  participate in the management of industries & to protect and improve the environment and  to safeguard forests and wildlife  "},
{ "id" : 66, "question" : "In the event of non-enforcement of DPSP by the Government, a citizen of India can move  the", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 67, "question" : "Provisions for a welfare State in India are found in ", "answer" : " DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 68, "question" : "In Gandhian Socialism, ", "answer" : " State is required  "},
{ "id" : 69, "question" : "Which of the following statements regard to the DPSPs is correct? ", "answer" : " The courts can  compel the State to implement some of the important directives  "},
{ "id" : 70, "question" : "Which one of the following DPSP is a socialistic principle? ", "answer" : " Prevention of  concentration of wealth and the means of production, Protection of the health of workers &  Equal pay for equal work to all  "},
{ "id" : 71, "question" : "The purpose of the inclusion of DPSP in the Indian Constitution is to establish ", "answer" : " Social  and Economic democracy   "},
{ "id" : 72, "question" : "DPSPs are the conscience of the Constitution, which embody the social philosophy of the  Constitution. The above statement was stated by: ", "answer" : "  Granville Austin  "},
{ "id" : 73, "question" : "Slow implementation of DPSPs in due to ", "answer" : "  Lack of political will     ******************************************************************************************                    IV. FUNDAMENTAL DUTIES (FDs)  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "The concept of FDs are borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " Russia  "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "Which Committee recommended for the inclusion of FDs into the Constitution? ", "answer" : " Sardar  Swaran Singh  "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "The FDs under the Indian Constitution are provided by ", "answer" : "  An Amendment to the  Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "FDs are applicable to all ", "answer" : " Citizens   "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "The FDs of the Indian citizens were ", "answer" : " Added to the Constitution by 42nd Amendment  (11.12.1976)  "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "The FDs of Indian citizens were incorporated in the Constitution in ", "answer" : " 1976  "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "FD demands to ", "answer" : " Abide by the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "This is not a FD. ", "answer" : "  Not to indulge in corrupt practice  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "For the breach of FD, an action ", "answer" : "  cannot be initiated in any Court  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "What is the remedy available for the breach of FDs under the Constitution? ", "answer" : " Filing writ  petition   "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "FDs were incorporated in the Constitution to ", "answer" : " curb subversive and unconstitutional  activities  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "The FDs of citizens ", "answer" : "  are contained in Part IV-A of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "Which one of the following is being included in the Part IV-A of the Constitution? ", "answer" : "   FDs  "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "FDs are enshrined under _____ Part of the Constitution. ", "answer" : "  IV-A  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "Under which Article the FDs are enshrined under the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : "  51A   "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "The ratio between the length and breadth of the Indian National Flag is ", "answer" : " 3:2   "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "Respecting our National Flag is a ", "answer" : " FD   "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "To respect the National Flag and National Anthem is ", "answer" : " FDs of every citizen  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "National Song ‘Bande Matharam’ was written in 1875 by Bankimchandra Chatterjee in his  novel ", "answer" : " Anand Math   "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "India’s National Anthem ‘Jana gana mana’ was adopted by the Constituent Assembly as  the National Anthem of India on 24th January 1950 and was first sung on ", "answer" : " 27th December,  1911   "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "The National Flag of India is a horizontal tri-color of deep Saffron (Kesari-representing  courage and sacrifice) at the top, White (peace and truth) in the middle and deep Green (faith and  chivalry) at the bottom in equal proportion and in the center Wheel (representing progression) was  adopted by the Constituent Assembly of India on ", "answer" : " 22.07.1947   "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "The protection and improvement of environment including forest and wildlife of the  country is enshrined in ", "answer" : "  FDs & DPSP   "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "The duty to protect and improve the environment is enshrined under the Article ", "answer" : " 51A (g)  "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "Which of the following is a FD of an Indian citizen? ", "answer" : " To develop scientific temper  "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "What is the main sanction behind the FDs? ", "answer" : " Legal   "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Which FD has been wrongly listed as a duty of Indian citizen as outlined in Article 51A? ", "answer" : " To practice family planning and control population  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "By what Amendment and with Year ‘Child education is compulsory between ages of 06-14  years’? ", "answer" : " 86 th  and 2002   "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "Obligation of the parents / guardian to provide opportunities for the education to their  children between 6 to 14 years of age is ", "answer" : " FDs   "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "Which one of the following is / are FDs? ", "answer" : " To uphold and protect the sovereignty of  India, To safeguard the public property & To protect and improve environment  "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "The FDs cannot be enforced by writs, they can be promoted by _____ method. ", "answer" : "   Constitutional   "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "The original text of the Constitution doesn’t contain FDs, however it is inserted by way of  ____ Amendment. ", "answer" : " 42nd   "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "The 42nd Amendment introduced ", "answer" : " FDs   "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "It is the duty of every citizen if India to promote harmony and the spirit of common  brotherhood amongst all people of India under Article ", "answer" : " 51A (e)   "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "FD under Article 51A (k) was inserted to the Constitution by ____ Amendment Act, 2002.  ", "answer" : " 86th   "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "FDs refers to ", "answer" : " (i) Ideals of the national struggle & (ii) Defend the country and  render national service  "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Consider the following statements – The FDs provided in Constitution are (As per Article  51A) ", "answer" : "    (i) To protect the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India & (ii) To protect and  improve the natural environment including forests, lakes, rivers and wild life  "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "The purpose of FD is to ", "answer" : " Develop scientific temper              V. UNION / CENTRAL GOVERNMENT  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "The President of Indian Union has the similar Constitutional authority as the ", "answer" : " British  Monarch   "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India was created by ", "answer" : " The Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "The concept of Judicial Review has been borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : "  Switzerland   "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "The Seat of Supreme Court is ", "answer" : " New Delhi  "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "Can a retired judge be asked to sit in the Supreme Court? ", "answer" : " Yes   "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "Which of the following is not one of the three organs of the Union / State? ", "answer" : " Press   "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "Which of the following is considered as the Fourth Estate? ", "answer" : "  Press  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "The organ of the State which makes law is ", "answer" : " Legislature   "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "The organ of the State implement and execute laws is known as ", "answer" : " Executive  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "‘Legislate’ means ", "answer" : " make law  "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "‘Natural Justice’ means ", "answer" : "  just, fair and reasonable action  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "Which of the following is not a function of judiciary? ", "answer" : " Catching criminals and  punishing them  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "Article 254 of the Constitution deals with ", "answer" : " dominance of Union laws over State laws  in case of any conflict between the two  "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "Under the Indian Constitution, the subjects of administration have been divided into ", "answer" : "  Three lists  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "India is known as a Parliamentary Democracy because the ", "answer" : " Executive is responsible to  the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "In Parliamentary form of Government, the Council of Ministers are responsible to the ", "answer" : "  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "The President of India is an integral part of the ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "The Parliament may confer by law any functions on the authorities concerned except the ", "answer" : " - President  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "All the Executive powers and the Defence forces of the Union shall be vested in the ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "In India, Mandamus will lie against ", "answer" : "  Both Officers and Government   "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "The power to establish new states in India rests with the ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "When can the President refer a matter to the Supreme Court for its opinion? ", "answer" : " When a  matter is of public importance  "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "Which of the following is not a writ issued only by a superior court to an inferior court? ", "answer" : " - Certiorari   "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "The Supreme Court propounded ‘The Theory of Basic Structure of the Constitution’ in", "answer" : "  Keshavananda Bharti case   "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "How many judges sat on the Bench to hear the landmark case of Keshavananda Bharti V/s  State of Kerala in 1973? ", "answer" : " 13  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Which of the following is not a constitutionally mandatory body? (Commission for) ", "answer" : "  Center-State Relations  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "The Appellate Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court does not involve in ", "answer" : " Disputes arising  out of pre-constitution treaties and agreements  "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "In India, the power of Judicial Review is enjoyed by the ", "answer" : " Supreme Court only  "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "The Chief Justice and other Judges of the High Court are appointed by the ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "In criminal matters, the highest court of appeal in a district is the ", "answer" : " Court of Second  Class Magistrate   "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "A High Court for two or more States and or Union Territory may be established by ", "answer" : "  Law by Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Golden Jubilee of Indian Parliament was celebrated on ", "answer" : "  13.05.2002   "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "Who is the integral part of the Indian Parliament? ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "Who represents the Nation but does not rule the Nation? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "In the Presidential Election (Electoral College) ", "answer" : " Parity between the Center and the  States has been maintained  "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Indian Constitution has distributed the powers between the Center and _______. ", "answer" : "  States   "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "Who is the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : " The Vice President   "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "The Speaker is elected by the Members of ________. ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "The President of India is ", "answer" : " Elected   "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "Who elects the President of India? ", "answer" : "  By Electoral College  "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "How many times the President can seek re-election to his post? ", "answer" : " Infinite times   "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "Who acts as the President when neither the President nor the Vice President is available? ", "answer" : " Chief Justice of India   "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "In the Presidential Election in India, every elected member of the Legislative Assembly of a  State shall have as many votes as there multiples of one ______ in the quotient obtained by  dividing the population of the state by the total number of elected members of the assembly. ", "answer" : "  Thousand   "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "A Bill for the purpose of altering the boundaries of any State shall be introduced in either of  the House of the Parliament with the recommendation of the _______. ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "Which is the Committee recommended for the Reorganization of States? ", "answer" : "  Fazal Ali  "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "Which Act has been enacted by the Parliament by exercising its power under the Article 3  of the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  States Reorganization Act   "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "States will be reorganized by the Parliament under the Article 3 of the Constitution on the - ", "answer" : "  Linguistic basis   "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "A Bill for the purpose of reorganization of states shall be introduced in either of House of  the Parliament with the prior approval of the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "India opted for a Federal form of government on the ground of ", "answer" : " Linguistic and  Regional diversity   "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "Who is the Commander-in-Chief of all the Armed Forces? ", "answer" : " The President   "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "What is the eligibility age and tenure of Office of President and Vice President? (in years) - ", "answer" : " 35 and 5  "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "How many Members can be elected for Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : " 552 & 238  "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "How many Anglo-Indian and other Members can be nominated by the President to the Lok  Sabha and Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : "  2 and 12   "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "How many States and Union Territories are there in our country? ", "answer" : "  28 and 7   "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "In which year, Delhi got the status of a State? ", "answer" : "  1993   "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "How many seats are reserved for the members of the Scheduled Tribes in the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  30  "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "Which of the following became the 28th State of the Indian Union? ", "answer" : " Jharkhand   "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "Who will preside over the Joint Session of both the Houses of the Parliament? ", "answer" : " Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "Which of the following appointments is not made by the President of the Indian Republic?  ", "answer" : "  Speaker of Lok Sabha   "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "The President will decide the question as to disqualification of the MPs in consultation with  the ", "answer" : " Election Commissioner  "},
{ "id" : 61, "question" : "Which Article empowers the President to give his assent to Bills? ", "answer" : " 111   "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "Which Article authorizes the President to seek an advice from the Supreme Court? ", "answer" : " 143   "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "In a Federation, the source of power for the States is the ", "answer" : " Constitution   "},
{ "id" : 64, "question" : "How the Constitution of India has distributed the powers to different levels? ", "answer" : "  Concurrent List, Central List & State List  "},
{ "id" : 65, "question" : "How many subjects are there in the Central, State and Concurrent Lists? ", "answer" : " 97, 66 and 47   "},
{ "id" : 66, "question" : "The Central, State and Concurrent Lists indicates division of ", "answer" : " Legislative powers  "},
{ "id" : 67, "question" : "Economic Planning is a subject in the ", "answer" : " Concurrent List   "},
{ "id" : 68, "question" : "Railways is a subject under ____ ", "answer" : " Union List  "},
{ "id" : 69, "question" : "Lotteries organized by the State Government come under _____ List. ", "answer" : "  State  "},
{ "id" : 70, "question" : "Distribution of subjects between the Center and the States is enumerated under ____  Schedule. ", "answer" : " 7th   "},
{ "id" : 71, "question" : "Sarkaria Commission was appointed by the Government to report on ", "answer" : " Center-State  Relations   "},
{ "id" : 72, "question" : "Planning in India derives its objectives from ", "answer" : " DPSP  "},
{ "id" : 73, "question" : "Which of the taxes is exclusively assigned to Central Government by the Constitution? ", "answer" : "   Corporation Tax  "},
{ "id" : 74, "question" : "The other names for Rajya Sabha (Permanent Body) are ", "answer" : "  Upper House / House of  States   "},
{ "id" : 75, "question" : "The other names for Lok Sabha (Temporary Body) are ", "answer" : "  Lower House / House of  People  "},
{ "id" : 76, "question" : "The word ‘Parliament’ is derived from the French word ‘Parler’ which means ", "answer" : " To talk   "},
{ "id" : 77, "question" : "Parliament of India is composed of ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha and President  "},
{ "id" : 78, "question" : "The first session of the Parliament after the General Election is ", "answer" : " Mandatory   "},
{ "id" : 79, "question" : "The first session of the Parliament is called as ______ Session. ", "answer" : "  Budget  "},
{ "id" : 80, "question" : "Lok Sabha is superior to the Rajya Sabha because ", "answer" : " (i) it can oust the Council of  Ministers through a vote of no-confidence, (ii) it is directly elected & (iii) it alone controls the  purse  "},
{ "id" : 81, "question" : "How many MPs of Lok Sabha shall support a motion of ‘No Confidence’ in the  government, before it can be admitted by the Speaker? ", "answer" : " 50   "},
{ "id" : 82, "question" : "Which among the following is identified as the ‘Democratic Chamber’? ", "answer" : "  Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 83, "question" : "Which among the following is described as ‘Knowledge House’? ", "answer" : "  Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 84, "question" : "Composition and function of Rajya Sabha points towards ________ Character. ", "answer" : "   Federal   "},
{ "id" : 85, "question" : "What is the method of electing members of Rajya Sabha from Union Territories? ", "answer" : "  as  law laid down by the Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 86, "question" : "The representation to the States in the Rajya Sabha is given by ", "answer" : " in proportion to the  State population  "},
{ "id" : 87, "question" : "Which of the following is not done by the Parliament? ", "answer" : "  Adjournment of the Houses  of the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 88, "question" : "The President of India may from time to time ", "answer" : " dissolve the Lok Sabha   "},
{ "id" : 89, "question" : "The President and Governors are immune from ____ during their term of Office. ", "answer" : "  Civil  liability  "},
{ "id" : 90, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution gives the protection to the President and Governors? ", "answer" : " -  361  "},
{ "id" : 91, "question" : "To contest for the election of Lok Sabha, the person ", "answer" : "  should be citizen of India  "},
{ "id" : 92, "question" : "An Ordinance promulgated by the President when one House is in session is ", "answer" : "  Valid  "},
{ "id" : 93, "question" : "The Ordinance making power of the President is subjected to the control of the ", "answer" : "  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 94, "question" : "An Ordinance can be promulgated on the subject mentioned in ", "answer" : " List I and List III   "},
{ "id" : 95, "question" : "Parliament has exclusive power to make laws with respect to any matter enumerated In ", "answer" : "  List I   "},
{ "id" : 96, "question" : "State Legislature has exclusive power to make laws with respect to any matter enumerated  in ", "answer" : " List II   "},
{ "id" : 97, "question" : "If any matter is not enumerated either under the Concurrent List or under State List then  who has the power to legislate on such matters? ", "answer" : "  Parliament only  "},
{ "id" : 98, "question" : "Who has the power to make laws on the subjects enumerated under List III of 7 th  Schedule?  ", "answer" : "  Both Parliament and State Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 99, "question" : "A Resolution passed by the Rajya Sabha empowering the Parliament to legislate under List  II on National interest should be supported by ", "answer" : " Two-third members present and voting  "},
{ "id" : 100, "question" : "Parliament has power to legislate under the State List on the ground of National Interest if  ", "answer" : "  Rajya Sabha passes a Resolution to that effect  "},
{ "id" : 101, "question" : "A Resolution passed by the Rajya Sabha empowering the Parliament to legislate under  State List shall remain in force for a maximum period of ", "answer" : " One year  "},
{ "id" : 102, "question" : "Law made by the Parliament on any subject is ", "answer" : "  Uniformly applicable to all States  "},
{ "id" : 103, "question" : "The law made by the Parliament ", "answer" : "  Cannot be declared as extra-territorial  "},
{ "id" : 104, "question" : "If the law made by the Parliament is inconsistent with the law made by the State  Legislature under the List III, which law has the effect? ", "answer" : "  Law made by the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 105, "question" : "A Fund which is utilized to meet the unforeseen expenditure is entitled as ", "answer" : "  Contingency Fund   "},
{ "id" : 106, "question" : "The usual expenditure of the Government of India is charged from ", "answer" : " Consolidated  Fund   "},
{ "id" : 107, "question" : "The Custody of Contingency Fund of India is with the ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 108, "question" : "What is the term of the Parliamentary Committees appointed by the President? ", "answer" : " One  year  "},
{ "id" : 109, "question" : "A Select or Joint Committee of the two Houses of a Parliament is formed by ", "answer" : " Speaker  of the Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 110, "question" : "Which of the following has been wrongly listed as a Standing Joint Committee of the two  Houses of the Parliament? ", "answer" : " Committee on Government Assurances  "},
{ "id" : 111, "question" : "Which of the following Committees of the Parliament has the largest membership? ", "answer" : "   Estimate Committee   "},
{ "id" : 112, "question" : "Parliament Standing Committee for scrutiny of grants of various ministries comprises of ", "answer" : "  30 members of Lok Sabha and 15 members of Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 113, "question" : "The Parliamentary Subject Committees (Number of Committees: 17) were introduced in  1993 on the recommendation of the ", "answer" : " Rules Committee of the House  "},
{ "id" : 114, "question" : "The main advantage of the Standing Committee is the ", "answer" : "  Parliament is able to  examine the grants of all ministries and departments in detail  "},
{ "id" : 115, "question" : "One of the main advantage of the Standing Committee is ", "answer" : "  MPs of Rajya Sabha are  able to exercise indirect control over financial matters  "},
{ "id" : 116, "question" : "The Standing Committee, apart from examining the grant of all Ministries and  Departments, are able to examine", "answer" : " Long-term policies,  Bills of technical nature & Annual  reports of Ministries and Departments  "},
{ "id" : 117, "question" : "When an advance grant is made by Parliament pending regular passage of the Budget, it is  called ", "answer" : " Vote of Account   "},
{ "id" : 118, "question" : "Who is having the power to summon and dissolve the House of Parliament (LS)? ", "answer" : "   President  "},
{ "id" : 119, "question" : "Which Budget will be proposed first in the Parliament House? ", "answer" : "  Railway  "},
{ "id" : 120, "question" : "Usually, General Budget is presented to the Parliament on ", "answer" : " Last day of February   "},
{ "id" : 121, "question" : "The first session of the year commences with the address by the ______ in the Parliament.  ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 122, "question" : "The first hour of every sitting in both the Houses of Parliament is devoted to ", "answer" : "  Question Hour  "},
{ "id" : 123, "question" : "What are the timings followed for the Question Hour in the Parliament House? ", "answer" : " 11 to  12   "},
{ "id" : 124, "question" : "What are the timings followed for the Zero Hour in the Parliament House? ", "answer" : " 12 to 1   "},
{ "id" : 125, "question" : "The maximum duration of the Zero Hour (in minutes) in Lok Sabha can be ", "answer" : " 60 mint  "},
{ "id" : 126, "question" : "Zero Hour is ", "answer" : " The period immediately following the Question Hour when the  Members voice their concerns on various matters of public importance  "},
{ "id" : 127, "question" : "The immediate hour after the Question Hour in Lok Sabha is called as ", "answer" : "  Zero Hour  "},
{ "id" : 128, "question" : "Who presides over the joint sessions of Parliament? ", "answer" : " Speaker   "},
{ "id" : 129, "question" : "What is the minimum age in years for becoming the MP at Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha? - ", "answer" : " 25 and 30   "},
{ "id" : 130, "question" : "Which of the following shall not be introduced in the Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : " Money Bill  "},
{ "id" : 131, "question" : "The system of Impeachment of the President is borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : "  Britain  "},
{ "id" : 132, "question" : "Who can be removed for violation of Constitution by a process called as Impeachment  Motion? ", "answer" : "President  "},
{ "id" : 133, "question" : "The seat of a MP may be declared vacant, if he / she is, without the permission of the  House absent from the meeting of that House for a period of ______ days. ", "answer" : "  60   "},
{ "id" : 134, "question" : "Till now, any President has been removed under the Motion of Impeachment? ", "answer" : "  No   "},
{ "id" : 135, "question" : "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution can the President be impeached? ", "answer" : "  61  "},
{ "id" : 136, "question" : "Impeachment proceedings against the President shall be initiated in ", "answer" : " Either of the  Houses  "},
{ "id" : 137, "question" : "The ground for the Impeachment of President is ", "answer" : "  violation of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 138, "question" : "The Indian President can be impeached by the Parliament if ", "answer" : "  He is charged with the  violation of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 139, "question" : "Which one of the following takes part in the election of the President but has no role in his  impeachment? ", "answer" : "  State Legislative Assemblies  "},
{ "id" : 140, "question" : "The salary / emoluments of which of the following is exempted from Income Tax? ", "answer" : "   President   "},
{ "id" : 141, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is correct? ", "answer" : " President is not a part of Council  of Ministers and hence not permitted to attend its meetings  "},
{ "id" : 142, "question" : "A Bill presented in the Parliament becomes an Act after ", "answer" : " The President has given his  assent  "},
{ "id" : 143, "question" : "Who occupied the President’s Office twice (two consecutive terms) in our country? ", "answer" : "  Rajendra Prasad   "},
{ "id" : 144, "question" : "Veto is the power of the ________ to withhold or refuse assent to Legislation. ", "answer" : "   Executive   "},
{ "id" : 145, "question" : "Vice President of India draws salary in the designation of ", "answer" : " Chairman of Rajya  Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 146, "question" : "Who will elect the Vice President of India?  ", "answer" : "  MP (Rajya Sabha and Lok Sabha)   "},
{ "id" : 147, "question" : "Which of the following is presided over by a non-member? ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 148, "question" : "Full form of PIL is ", "answer" : " Public Interest Litigation  "},
{ "id" : 149, "question" : "PIL can be resorted to in case of injury due to ", "answer" : " Violation of a constitutional  provision, Breach of any public duty & Violation of the law   "},
{ "id" : 150, "question" : "The Concept of Public Interest Litigation, which has become more popular in India in  recent years, originated in ", "answer" : " UK   "},
{ "id" : 151, "question" : "Who has the power to pardon in case of capital punishment? ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 152, "question" : "Which Article empowers the President to grant pardon? ", "answer" : "72  "},
{ "id" : 153, "question" : "The pardoning power shall be exercised by the President on the advice of the ", "answer" : " Home  Minister  "},
{ "id" : 154, "question" : "Who is authorized to transfer the judge of one High Court to another High Court? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 155, "question" : "Which of the following Constitutional post(s) is / are enjoyed for a fixed term? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 156, "question" : "The Constitution of India vests the executive powers of the Union Government in ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 157, "question" : "Which Article empowers the President to appoint Prime Minister of India? ", "answer" : " 74   "},
{ "id" : 158, "question" : "Joint Session of Parliament was held in ", "answer" : "(i) Prevention of Terrorism Ordinance,  2002, (ii) Dowry Prohibition Bill, 1961 & (iii) Banking Service Commission Bill, 1978  "},
{ "id" : 159, "question" : "Joint Sittings of the two Houses of Parliament are hold for ", "answer" : "  Resolution of deadlock  between the two Houses on a non-money Bill  "},
{ "id" : 160, "question" : "The House of People (Lok Sabha) can be adjourned sine-die by the ", "answer" : " Speaker   "},
{ "id" : 161, "question" : "The President of India is the ", "answer" : " Head of State  "},
{ "id" : 162, "question" : "The President of India is ", "answer" : "  Elected through Electoral college  "},
{ "id" : 163, "question" : "The President holds Office for a term of five years ", "answer" : "  from the date on which he / she  enters upon the Office  "},
{ "id" : 164, "question" : "The practice of President addressing Parliament has been adopted from Constitution of ", "answer" : " - UK   "},
{ "id" : 165, "question" : "Which one of the following does not take part in the election of the President? ", "answer" : "  Members-Legislative Councils   "},
{ "id" : 166, "question" : "The name of the candidate for the Office of the President of India has to be proposed by ", "answer" : " any 50 members of the Electoral College  "},
{ "id" : 167, "question" : "Who was the first President of the Indian Republic? ", "answer" : "  Rajendra Prasad  "},
{ "id" : 168, "question" : "Who among following got Bharat Ratna Award before becoming the President of India? ", "answer" : " Radhakrishnan   "},
{ "id" : 169, "question" : "Who is the following enjoys the distinction of being the first Muslim President of India? ", "answer" : "  Zakir Hussain   "},
{ "id" : 170, "question" : "Which one of the following was elected President of India unopposed? ", "answer" : " Neelam  Sanjeeva Reddy  "},
{ "id" : 171, "question" : "Which one of the following political leaders successfully held the Office of the Chief  Minister, Speaker of Lok Sabha and President of India? ", "answer" : "  Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy   "},
{ "id" : 172, "question" : "Which one of the following Chief Justice of India enjoys the distinction of having acted as  President of India? ", "answer" : "  Justice M. Hidayatullah   "},
{ "id" : 173, "question" : "The election of the Office of the President is conducted by ", "answer" : "  Election Commission   "},
{ "id" : 174, "question" : "Before entering upon Office, the President has to take an oath or an affirmation, which is  administered by ", "answer" : " Chief Justice of India  "},
{ "id" : 175, "question" : "The procedure for the election of the President of India can be modified through an  Amendment in the Constitution which must be passed by ", "answer" : "  two-thirds majority by both Lok  Sabha and Rajya Sabha and be ratified by the Legislatures of at least half of the states  "},
{ "id" : 176, "question" : "To amend the Constitution to change the procedure of election of the President of India,  the Bill has to be passed by ", "answer" : "  Special majority, ratified by more than half of the States  "},
{ "id" : 177, "question" : "The President can nominate two members of the Lok Sabha to give representation to ", "answer" : "  Anglo-Indians  "},
{ "id" : 178, "question" : "The President, the Head of the State under the Parliamentary system prevailing in India,  enjoys ", "answer" : " only nominal powers  "},
{ "id" : 179, "question" : "The final authority to make a Proclamation of Emergency rests with ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 180, "question" : "The President can grant pardon in ", "answer" : " (i) All cases of punishment by court martial, (ii)  All cases involving death sentence & (iii) All offences against laws in the union and  concurrent lists  "},
{ "id" : 181, "question" : "The President of India is not having ", "answer" : " Power to control Judiciary  "},
{ "id" : 182, "question" : "Which one of the financial powers is enjoyed by the President? ", "answer" : " (i) Money Bills can  be introduced in the Parliament, (ii) The President appoints a Finance Commission to  recommend the distribution of taxes between Union and State Governments & (iii) The  President can advance money out of the Contingency Fund of India  "},
{ "id" : 183, "question" : "The President can make laws through ordinances ", "answer" : " during the recess of the  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 184, "question" : "Where are disputes regarding election of President and Vice President filed and settled? ", "answer" : " Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 185, "question" : "If the President wants to tender the resignation before expiry of normal term, he / she has  to address the same to ", "answer" : " Vice President   "},
{ "id" : 186, "question" : "The President of India is elected by Ele", "answer" : " cted MLAs and MPs   "},
{ "id" : 187, "question" : "To be eligible (age in years) for appointment as President, a candidate must be ", "answer" : " over  35  "},
{ "id" : 188, "question" : "When does the President uses his discretion in appointing the Prime Minister? ", "answer" : "  When  no political party enjoys majority in Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 189, "question" : "The Constitution prohibits to enact retrospectively ", "answer" : "  Laws relating to the election of  the President  "},
{ "id" : 190, "question" : "What is the maximum age (in years) for election to the Office of the President? ", "answer" : "  No  age limit  "},
{ "id" : 191, "question" : "President can be impeached from Office on grounds of violating the Constitution by ", "answer" : "  Two Houses of Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 192, "question" : "Impeachment proceedings against the President of India can be initiated ", "answer" : " in either of  the Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 193, "question" : "Impeachments proceedings can be initiated against the President in either of House of  Parliament only if a resolution signed by _______ members of the House is moved. ", "answer" : "  25% of  total   "},
{ "id" : 194, "question" : "This is not the legislative power of the President ", "answer" : "  to grant pardon   "},
{ "id" : 195, "question" : "When the election of the President is declared void, all acts done by the President in the  performance of the duties of his Office before the date of decision become ", "answer" : " valid  "},
{ "id" : 196, "question" : "In the event of death or resignation of the President, the Vice President discharges the  duties of the office of President ", "answer" : " For a maximum period of six months  "},
{ "id" : 197, "question" : "In case the Vice President is not available to discharge the duties of the Office of  President, which official discharges these duties? ", "answer" : "  Chief Justice of India   "},
{ "id" : 198, "question" : "Which one of the following Official discharges the duties of the President, if both the  President and Vice President are not available? ", "answer" : "  Chief Justice of India  "},
{ "id" : 199, "question" : "If the Office of the President, Vice President and Chief Justice of India falls vacant  simultaneously, who succeeds to the Office of the President? ", "answer" : " Next Senior-most Judge of  the Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 200, "question" : "When the Office of the President falls vacant, the same must be filled within ", "answer" : " six   "},
{ "id" : 201, "question" : "Who is legally competent to declare war or conclude peace? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 202, "question" : "After a Bill has been passed by Parliament and sent to the President for his consideration - ", "answer" : " He can sent it back for reconsideration  "},
{ "id" : 203, "question" : "The President can make laws through ordinances ", "answer" : "  During the recess of Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 204, "question" : "Ordinance is promulgated by the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 205, "question" : "What financial power is enjoyed by the President? ", "answer" : " (i) Certain Money Bills can  originate in Parliament only on the recommendation of the President, (ii) Only on the  recommendation of the Governor & (iii) He can appoint Finance Commission to recommend  the distribution of taxes between Union and State Governments  "},
{ "id" : 206, "question" : "Which one of the following officials is not appointed by the President? (OR) In the  appointment of which one of the following officials has the President no say? ", "answer" : "  District and  Sessions Judges  "},
{ "id" : 207, "question" : "The President of India made use of his / her veto power only once in the ", "answer" : " Indian Post  Office (Amendment) Bill   "},
{ "id" : 208, "question" : "An ordinance promulgated by the President usually remains in force for ", "answer" : " six weeks  after the commencement of the next session of the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 209, "question" : "The President can promulgate an ordinance only when ", "answer" : "  the Parliament is not in  session  "},
{ "id" : 210, "question" : "Proclamation of President’s Rule in a state can be made ", "answer" : "  if the President, on  receipt of a report from the Governor of a State or otherwise is satisfied that a situation has  arisen in which the government of the State cannot be carried on in accordance with the  provisions of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 211, "question" : "The President can dismiss a member of the Council of Ministers  on the ", "answer" : "  recommendation of the Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 212, "question" : "The Presidential Address is prepared by ", "answer" : " The Prime Minister and his / her Cabinet  "},
{ "id" : 213, "question" : "Who among the following are appointed by the President of India? ", "answer" : " 1. State  Governors, 2. Chief Justice and Judges of High Courts, 3. Chief Justice and Judges of  Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 214, "question" : "The President of India is elected on the basis of ", "answer" : " Proportional representation by  single-transferable vote  "},
{ "id" : 215, "question" : "Who will appoint the Attorney General of India? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 216, "question" : "The Vice President of India is ", "answer" : "  Elected by MPs (Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha) at  a joint sitting  "},
{ "id" : 217, "question" : "Vice President of India can be removed from Office before expiry of his / her term by ", "answer" : "   Two Houses of Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 218, "question" : "The Vice President of India discharges the duties of President in the event ", "answer" : " (i) His  death, (ii) His resignation & (iii) His absence due to illness  "},
{ "id" : 219, "question" : "The Vice President of India is the ex-officio Chairman of the ", "answer" : " Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 220, "question" : "Who decides disputes regarding the election of the Vice President? ", "answer" : "  Supreme Court   "},
{ "id" : 221, "question" : "The Vice President discharges the duties of the President during his / her illness for a  maximum period of ", "answer" : " Indefinitely  "},
{ "id" : 222, "question" : "When the Vice President discharges duties of Office of President, he is entitled to ", "answer" : "  Salary and allowances attached to the President’s Office  "},
{ "id" : 223, "question" : "The Vice President has ", "answer" : " Right to preside over Rajya Sabha   "},
{ "id" : 224, "question" : "No criminal proceedings shall be instituted during his term of Office against the ", "answer" : "  Vice President   "},
{ "id" : 225, "question" : "Among the four pairs given below, which one consists of correct combination of  dignitaries who became Vice Presidents after having held diplomatic positions? ", "answer" : "  S.  Radhakrishnan and G. S. Pathak   "},
{ "id" : 226, "question" : "Identify the correct order in which the following acted as Vice President of India: ", "answer" : "    "},
{ "id" : 227, "question" : "Which one of the following Vice President(s) resigned from his Office to contest for the  Office of the President? ", "answer" : " VV Giri  "},
{ "id" : 228, "question" : "Who of the following held the Office of the Vice President of India for two full terms? ", "answer" : " - Radhakrishnan  "},
{ "id" : 229, "question" : "Who of the following became President of India without serving as Vice President? ", "answer" : "   Sanjeeva Reddy   "},
{ "id" : 230, "question" : "Who is the first Chief Justice to be appointed as acting President of India? ", "answer" : "   Hidayatullah  "},
{ "id" : 231, "question" : "Which Article provides that there shall be the Prime Minister of India? ", "answer" : "  74  "},
{ "id" : 232, "question" : "The Prime Minister is ", "answer" : " Head of Government  "},
{ "id" : 233, "question" : "The Office of the Prime Minister ", "answer" : "  has been created by the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 234, "question" : "The Prime Minister is ", "answer" : "  appointed by the President  "},
{ "id" : 235, "question" : "Who is the real Executive under the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 236, "question" : "Who is considered as the Chief Spokesperson (Spokesman) of the Union Government? ", "answer" : " Prime Minister   "},
{ "id" : 237, "question" : "Who is the Chairman of the Planning Commission and National Development Council? ", "answer" : "  P M  "},
{ "id" : 238, "question" : "Generally, the Prime Minister is ", "answer" : "  Leader of the majority party in the Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 239, "question" : "The Prime Minister holds Office ", "answer" : "  As long as he enjoys confidence of Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 240, "question" : "Generally the Prime Minister is ", "answer" : " Member of Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 241, "question" : "Who announces the Government policies on the floor of the House? ", "answer" : " Prime Minister   "},
{ "id" : 242, "question" : "Who recommends for the dissolution of Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 243, "question" : "Who presides over the meetings of the Council of Ministers?  ", "answer" : " Prime Minister   "},
{ "id" : 244, "question" : "Who acts as the channel of communication between the President and Council of  Ministers? ", "answer" : "PM  "},
{ "id" : 245, "question" : "Who is the keystone of the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 246, "question" : "Who describes the Prime Minister of India as ‘Primus Inter Pares’ (first among equals)? ", "answer" : " Lord Morely  "},
{ "id" : 247, "question" : "The members of Council of Ministers are appointed by the ", "answer" : "  President on the advice  of the Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 248, "question" : "A person can be member of the Council of Ministers without being a MP for a maximum  period of ___ months. ", "answer" : " six  "},
{ "id" : 249, "question" : "Who enjoys distinction of having been the Prime Minister of India for longest duration? ", "answer" : "  Indira Gandhi  "},
{ "id" : 250, "question" : "Who became the Prime Minister of India without becoming a Union Cabinet Minister? ", "answer" : "  H. D. Deve Gowda   "},
{ "id" : 251, "question" : "Which State of India has contributed the maximum Prime Ministers? ", "answer" : "  Uttar Pradesh   "},
{ "id" : 252, "question" : "Maximum number of ‘No Confidence Motion’ were admitted and discussed during the  Prime Ministership of ", "answer" : " P. V. Narasimha Rao  "},
{ "id" : 253, "question" : "The first Prime Minister of India was appointed by the ", "answer" : " Governor General  "},
{ "id" : 254, "question" : "The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister ", "answer" : "  is an extra-constitutional growth  "},
{ "id" : 255, "question" : "Indian Constitution is silent on the concept of ", "answer" : " Deputy Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 256, "question" : "Who enjoys the distinction of being the first Deputy Prime Minister of India? ", "answer" : "   Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel  "},
{ "id" : 257, "question" : "Lal Krishnan Advani is the ______ Deputy Prime Minister. ", "answer" : "  7th   "},
{ "id" : 258, "question" : "Which one of the following Motion can be moved by the Government? ", "answer" : " Confidence  Motion  "},
{ "id" : 259, "question" : "Which one of the following statement is correct? The Prime Minister of India ", "answer" : " has  full discretion in the choice of persons who are to serve as Ministers in his Cabinet  "},
{ "id" : 260, "question" : "Which of the following enjoys the distinction of being the first recognized Leader of the  Opposition in the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : " Y. B. Chavan  "},
{ "id" : 261, "question" : "A political party is accorded status of an Opposition Party in Lok Sabha if it captures at  least ", "answer" : " 10% of seats   "},
{ "id" : 262, "question" : "‘Collective Responsibility of the Cabinet’ means all Ministers are collectively responsible  to (OR) The Union Council of Ministers are responsible to ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 263, "question" : "Who enforces collective responsibility amongst the Council of Ministers? ", "answer" : " Prime  Minister  "},
{ "id" : 264, "question" : "The phrase under the Article 74 “There shall be Council of Ministers with the Prime  Minister is its Head” is ", "answer" : " Mandatory  "},
{ "id" : 265, "question" : "Who presides over the meetings of the Council of Ministers? ", "answer" : "  Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 266, "question" : "The Council of Ministers is collectively responsible to ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 267, "question" : "Who allocates portfolios among the Council of Ministers? ", "answer" : "  President on the  recommendation of Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 268, "question" : "A member of Council of Ministers can be dismissed by the President ", "answer" : "  on the  recommendation of the Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 269, "question" : "The vote of ‘No confidence’ is passed against a Minister ", "answer" : "  The whole Council of  Ministers has to resign  "},
{ "id" : 270, "question" : "Though the Council of Ministers is collectively responsible to the Parliament, the  individual Ministers are responsible to ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 271, "question" : "The President of India is removed from Office by ", "answer" : " Impeachment  "},
{ "id" : 272, "question" : "The President of India is not bound by the aid and advice of the Council of Ministers in  the matter of appointment of ", "answer" : " Union Ministers  "},
{ "id" : 273, "question" : "The Parliament of India consists of ", "answer" : " President, Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 274, "question" : "Members of the Lok Sabha are ", "answer" : " Directly elected by the people  "},
{ "id" : 275, "question" : "How many seats have been reserved for the Union Territories in the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : " 20  "},
{ "id" : 276, "question" : "The number of Ministers in the Central Government is fixed by the ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 277, "question" : "Seats are allocated to the various States in the Lok Sabha on the basis of ", "answer" : "  their  population  "},
{ "id" : 278, "question" : "Who among the following can initiate an amendment to the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Either House of Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 279, "question" : "Which State sends the maximum representatives to the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  Uttar Pradesh  "},
{ "id" : 280, "question" : "The 42nd Amendment raised the term of the Lok Sabha to _____ years. ", "answer" : " six   "},
{ "id" : 281, "question" : "The term of Lok Sabha can be extended beyond its normal term of five years by the ", "answer" : "  President during National Emergency only  "},
{ "id" : 282, "question" : "The President can extend the life of the Lok Sabha during a National Emergency in the  first instance for a period of ______ months. ", "answer" : "  one  "},
{ "id" : 283, "question" : "The Rajya Sabha can be dissolved by ", "answer" : " Cannot be dissolved  "},
{ "id" : 284, "question" : "The continuation of National Emergency beyond a period of six months is possible only  with the approval of ", "answer" : " Parliament by special majority  "},
{ "id" : 285, "question" : "What is the maximum gap in months permissible between two sessions of Parliament? ", "answer" : "  Six  "},
{ "id" : 286, "question" : "Who can dissolve the Lok Sabha before the expiry of its normal term of five years? ", "answer" : "  President on the recommendation of the Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 287, "question" : "Which of the following statements correctly describes a ‘Hung Parliament’? ", "answer" : "  A  Parliament in which no party has a clear majority  "},
{ "id" : 288, "question" : "The President can call a joint session of the two Houses of Parliament. ", "answer" : " (i) If the  House does not take any decision for six months on a Bill remitted by the other, (ii) If a Bill   passed by one House is rejected by the other & (iii) If the Amendment proposed to a Bill by  one House is not acceptable to the other  "},
{ "id" : 289, "question" : "In the Rajya Sabha, the States have been provided ", "answer" : "  Representation on the basis of  population  "},
{ "id" : 290, "question" : "The maximum number of representatives are sent to the Rajya Sabha by ", "answer" : " Uttar  Pradesh  "},
{ "id" : 291, "question" : "The members of Rajya Sabha shall be elected by ", "answer" : " MLAs  "},
{ "id" : 292, "question" : "Who reserves the right to convene joint sessions of the Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 293, "question" : "Representatives of the Union Territories in the Rajya Sabha shall be chosen by the ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 294, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a Central tax? ", "answer" : "  Sales Tax  "},
{ "id" : 295, "question" : "A Money Bill can originate ", "answer" : " Only in the Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 296, "question" : "Which of the following Bills can be introduced in the Parliament only with the prior  approval of the President? ", "answer" : "  Money Bills  "},
{ "id" : 297, "question" : "A Bill for which the President is bound to give his assent without sending it back for fresh  consideration is ", "answer" : " Money Bill  "},
{ "id" : 298, "question" : "Which one of the following Bills must be passed by each House of the Indian Parliament  separately, by special majority? ", "answer" : "  Constitution Amendment Bill  "},
{ "id" : 299, "question" : "How many times the President can return a Non-Money Bill, passed by the Parliament for  its consideration? ", "answer" : "  Once  "},
{ "id" : 300, "question" : "The Rajya Sabha is a Permanent House but ", "answer" : "  One-third of its members retire two  years  "},
{ "id" : 301, "question" : "A Money Bill passed by the Lok Sabha can be delayed by the Rajya Sabha for a  maximum period of ", "answer" : "14 days   "},
{ "id" : 302, "question" : "Which of the following sets of Bills is presented to the Parliament along with Budget? ", "answer" : " -  Finance Bill and Appropriation Bill   "},
{ "id" : 303, "question" : "Salary of which one of the Officials is not charged on the Consolidated Fund of India? ", "answer" : "   Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 304, "question" : "A Minister must be a Member of ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 305, "question" : "The Prime Minister acts as a channel of communication between ", "answer" : " Ministry and  President  "},
{ "id" : 306, "question" : "Cabinet Ministers has to tender its resignation if a no-confidence vote is passed against it  by ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 307, "question" : "In which system, the government can be removed by way of ‘No Confidence Motion’? ", "answer" : "  Parliamentary   "},
{ "id" : 308, "question" : "Who will determine the rank of different Ministers in Union and State Council of  Ministers? ", "answer" : " Prime Minister and Chief Minister  "},
{ "id" : 309, "question" : "Which of the following powers is exclusively vested in the Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : " To  recommend the creation of new All India Services  "},
{ "id" : 310, "question" : "The Rajya Sabha can be dissolved before expiry of its term by the ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 311, "question" : "Who is the first woman film star nominated or elected to Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : " Nargis Dutt  "},
{ "id" : 312, "question" : "No taxes can be levied or expenditure incurred without the approval of the ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 313, "question" : "Who decides disputes regarding the disqualification of MPs? ", "answer" : "  The President in  consultation with Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 314, "question" : "Election to the Lok Sabha could not be held in Punjab in December 1984 due to ", "answer" : "  Uncertainties created by growing terrorist activities  "},
{ "id" : 315, "question" : "Who decides whether a Bill is a Money Bill or not? (OR) If any question arises whether a  Bill is Money Bill or not, the decision of the _____ is final. ", "answer" : "  Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 316, "question" : "All Money Bills can be introduced ", "answer" : " in Lok Sabha only  "},
{ "id" : 317, "question" : "Who is the first Speaker of the Lok Sabha who died in Office? ", "answer" : " G.M.C. Balayogi  "},
{ "id" : 318, "question" : "Who presides over the Lok Sabha if neither the Speaker nor the Deputy Speaker is  available? ", "answer" : " A Member appointed by President  "},
{ "id" : 319, "question" : "If there is a disagreement between the two Houses of the Parliament on any particular Bill  ", "answer" : "  A Joint sitting of the two Houses of Parliament is convened  "},
{ "id" : 320, "question" : "In the Indian Constitution, the Budget is referred as ", "answer" : " Annual Financial Statement  "},
{ "id" : 321, "question" : "During the discussions in Parliament, ‘Guillotine’ applies to ", "answer" : " Demands for Grants   "},
{ "id" : 322, "question" : "Which Assembly is presided over by a non-member? ", "answer" : " Rajya Sabha   "},
{ "id" : 323, "question" : "The Chairman of the Rajya Sabha has ", "answer" : "  a vote only in case of tie  "},
{ "id" : 324, "question" : "The Secretary General of the Lok Sabha, who is the Chief of the Lok Sabha Secretariat, is  appointed by ", "answer" : " Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 325, "question" : "The Parliament of India cannot be regarded as a sovereign body because ", "answer" : " (i) of the  presence of certain fundamental rights of the citizens, (ii) its authority is confined to  jurisdiction earmarked by the Constitution & (iii) laws passed by Parliament can be  declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 326, "question" : "The Parliament of India exercises control over administration ", "answer" : " through  Parliamentary Committees  "},
{ "id" : 327, "question" : "The speech made by a MP on the floor of House", "answer" : "cannot be questioned in any  Court of Law  "},
{ "id" : 328, "question" : "The Parliament works through numerous committees, whose members are ", "answer" : " Either  appointed by the Speaker or elected by the House  "},
{ "id" : 329, "question" : "This is not the function of Lok Sabha. ", "answer" : " Judicial  "},
{ "id" : 330, "question" : "The Speaker of the Lok Sabha makes use of his / her casting vote only ", "answer" : " in case of tie  i.e. when votes are equally divided  "},
{ "id" : 331, "question" : "Lok Sabha Secretariat works under the direct supervision of the ", "answer" : " Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 332, "question" : "Lok Sabha passes vote on account to ", "answer" : "     meet the expenditure during the period  between the introduction of budget and its passage  "},
{ "id" : 333, "question" : "Which State sends the maximum number of representatives to the Rajya Sabha? ", "answer" : "   Uttar Pradesh  "},
{ "id" : 334, "question" : "A half an hour discussion can be raised in the House after giving notice to the ", "answer" : "  Secretary General of the House  "},
{ "id" : 335, "question" : "A MP enjoys immunity from prosecution for having said anything ", "answer" : " in the  Parliament and its Committees  "},
{ "id" : 336, "question" : "The final decision whether a MP of Lok Sabha has incurred disqualification under the  Defection Law rests with the ", "answer" : " Speaker   "},
{ "id" : 337, "question" : "The Parliament or State Legislature can declare a seat vacant if a member absents himself  without permission from the sessions for _____ days. ", "answer" : "  60  "},
{ "id" : 338, "question" : "Who presides over the Lok Sabha if neither Speaker nor Deputy Speaker is available? ", "answer" : " - a member of the panel of Chairmen announced by Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 339, "question" : "The function of the Pro-Temp Speaker is to ", "answer" : "  swear-in members and hold charge  till a regular Speaker is elected  "},
{ "id" : 340, "question" : "Which one of the following are the Financial Committees of Parliament of India?", "answer" : " 1.  Public Accounts Committee, 2. Estimate Committee & 3. Committee on Public Undertakings  "},
{ "id" : 341, "question" : "The Public Accounts Committee submits its report to the ", "answer" : " Speaker   "},
{ "id" : 342, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General acts as friend, philosopher and guide of ", "answer" : "  Public Accounts Committee  "},
{ "id" : 343, "question" : "Which one of the following motions is related with the Union Budget? ", "answer" : " Cut Motion  "},
{ "id" : 344, "question" : "Which of the following Committees of Parliament is concerned with the regularity and  economy of expenditure? ", "answer" : "  Public Accounts Committee   "},
{ "id" : 345, "question" : "Who of the following is considered the Custodian of the Parliament? ", "answer" : " Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 346, "question" : "A member, after being elected as Speaker of Lok Sabha, generally ", "answer" : " cuts-off his  connection with his party  "},
{ "id" : 347, "question" : "Which one of the following is the correct definition of the term ‘Whip’?", "answer" : "  State in  which all the members of the political party are required to be present in the Parliament and  vote according to the instructions of the party  "},
{ "id" : 348, "question" : "Who among the following may belong to Rajya Sabha but can speak in both the Houses? - ", "answer" : " Ministers who are MPs of Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 349, "question" : "Which one of the following statements regarding the Office of the Speaker is correct? ", "answer" : " - if he intends to resign, the letter of his resignation is to be addressed to the Deputy Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 350, "question" : "Which of the following statement is correct? ", "answer" : " the term of the Lok Sabha can be  extended by one year at a time  "},
{ "id" : 351, "question" : "Which one of the following Lok Sabha enjoyed a term of more than five years? ", "answer" : " 5th  "},
{ "id" : 352, "question" : "The differences between the two Houses of Parliament are resolved through (OR)  Disagreement between the two Houses of the Indian Parliament is finally resolved by which of the  following processes? ", "answer" : "  a joint session of the two Houses  "},
{ "id" : 353, "question" : "The quorum or minimum number of members required to hold the meeting of either  House of Parliament is ", "answer" : " one-tenth  "},
{ "id" : 354, "question" : "Which of the following States sends the largest number of MPs to Lok Sabha after Uttar  Pradesh? ", "answer" : "  Maharashtra   "},
{ "id" : 355, "question" : "Which of the following statements is not correct? ", "answer" : "  In the event of the dissolution of  the Lok Sabha, any Bill pending in the Rajya Sabha, but not passed by the Lok Sabha, lapses  "},
{ "id" : 356, "question" : "Under the new Committee system launched in April 1993, out of the 17 Standing  Committees ", "answer" : " 6 are constituted by the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha and 11 by the  Speaker of the Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 357, "question" : "The term ‘closure’ in Parliamentary terminology ", "answer" : " stoppage of debate on a motion  "},
{ "id" : 358, "question" : "‘No Confidence’ motion against Council of Ministers can be introduced in the ", "answer" : " Lok  Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 359, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India consists of a Chief Justice and _____ Judges. ", "answer" : " 30  "},
{ "id" : 360, "question" : "Who is the first Chief Justice of India? ", "answer" : " Harlal J. Kania   "},
{ "id" : 361, "question" : "The following factor does not help to maintain independence of judiciary ", "answer" : "  highly  attractive retirement benefits  "},
{ "id" : 362, "question" : "The Principles of Natural Justice do not require ", "answer" : " follow instructions strictly by  superior officer  "},
{ "id" : 363, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India was set up ", "answer" : " By the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 364, "question" : "Which is the highest Court of appeal in India? ", "answer" : " Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 365, "question" : "Who interprets the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : " Supreme Court   "},
{ "id" : 366, "question" : "Which Article provides that laws laid down by Supreme Court is binding on all courts in  India? ", "answer" : " 141  "},
{ "id" : 367, "question" : "Which Article empowers the Supreme Court to review its own judgment? ", "answer" : "137  "},
{ "id" : 368, "question" : "The Judges of the Supreme Court are appointed by the ", "answer" : " President in consultation  with the Chief Justice of India  "},
{ "id" : 369, "question" : "The Judges of the Supreme Court hold Office till they attain the age (in years) of ", "answer" : " 65   "},
{ "id" : 370, "question" : "One of the qualifications to become the Judge of the Supreme Court is ", "answer" : "  In the  opinion of the President, he must be a distinguished Jurist  "},
{ "id" : 371, "question" : "The Supreme Court holds its meetings at New Delhi, but it can meet elsewhere ", "answer" : " With  the approval of the President  "},
{ "id" : 372, "question" : "For criminal misconduct, the Judge of the Supreme Court ", "answer" : "  can be prosecuted  "},
{ "id" : 373, "question" : "The Judges of Supreme Court, after retirement, are not permitted to carry on practice  before", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 374, "question" : "In the event of non-availability of Chief Justice of India, an Acting Chief Justice can be  appointed by the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 375, "question" : "The Judges of the Supreme Court ", "answer" : "  can be removed by the President on the  recommendation of the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 376, "question" : "The Judges of the Supreme Court can be removed on the ground of proved misbehavior  by the _____ if the Parliament passes a resolution with two-third majority present and voting. ", "answer" : "   President   "},
{ "id" : 377, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India is a court of record which implies that ", "answer" : " (i) All its  decisions have evidentiary value and cannot be questioned in any court & (ii) It has power to  punish for its contempt  "},
{ "id" : 378, "question" : "The Supreme Court tenders advice to the President on a matter of law or fact ", "answer" : " only if  he seeks such advice  "},
{ "id" : 379, "question" : "The advice of the Supreme Court is ", "answer" : "  not binding on the President  "},
{ "id" : 380, "question" : "All cases involving an interpretation of the Constitution fall within the ", "answer" : " Original  jurisdiction of the Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 381, "question" : "Power of the Supreme Court to decide disputes between the Center and States fall under  its ", "answer" : "Original Jurisdiction  "},
{ "id" : 382, "question" : "Original Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of India relates to ", "answer" : " Disputes between  Union and States  "},
{ "id" : 383, "question" : "The Supreme Court has Original Jurisdiction in ", "answer" : " All Inter-State disputes  "},
{ "id" : 384, "question" : "Under the Advisory Jurisdiction, the Supreme Court gives it’s opinion to the ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 385, "question" : "Appellate Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court does not include ", "answer" : " appeals against writs   "},
{ "id" : 386, "question" : "Appellate Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court in appeal from High Court in regard to civil  matters pertaining only to ", "answer" : " Substantial question of law  "},
{ "id" : 387, "question" : "Who has the power to enlarge the Jurisdiction of Supreme Court with respect to any  matter contained under the Union List? ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 388, "question" : "Which of the following statement refers to ‘Epistolary Jurisdiction’ of the Supreme Court?  ", "answer" : " Taking cognizance of the concerned matter through letter addressed to the Court  "},
{ "id" : 389, "question" : "Who has the power to increase the number of Judges of the Supreme Court? ", "answer" : "  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 390, "question" : "Ad hoc Judges can be appointed in the Supreme Court by the ", "answer" : " Chief Justice of  India with the prior consent of the President  "},
{ "id" : 391, "question" : "Ad hoc Judges can be appointed to the Supreme Court ", "answer" : " if requisite number of  Judges are not available to hold the meeting of the Court  "},
{ "id" : 392, "question" : "How many Judges of the Supreme Court have been removed from their Office before the  expiry of their normal term through Impeachment? ", "answer" : "  none   "},
{ "id" : 393, "question" : "Which of the following has been wrongly listed as criteria for appointment as a Judge of  the Supreme Court? ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 394, "question" : "Which conditions does not contribute to the independence of the Indian Judiciary? ", "answer" : "  Once appointed, the Judges cannot be removed from their Office before the date of  retirement  "},
{ "id" : 395, "question" : "Which of the following statements regarding Supreme Court of India is not correct? ", "answer" : "   Acts as the protector of the Directive Principles of State Policy  "},
{ "id" : 396, "question" : "Which of the following cases was connected with the Supreme Court’s judgment in 1980  that the Amendments made to Articles 31 (c) and 368 are invalid? ", "answer" : "  Keshavananda Bharti  Case  "},
{ "id" : 397, "question" : "In which Case did the Supreme Court restore the primacy of Fundamental Rights over  Directive Principles of State Policy? ", "answer" : " Minerva Mills Case  "},
{ "id" : 398, "question" : "Any Act violating Article 13(2) of the Constitution shall be declared as Unconstitutional  by ", "answer" : "Supreme Court   "},
{ "id" : 399, "question" : "‘Appeal by Special Leave’ means ", "answer" : " Supreme Court, granting in its discretion  special permission to appeal from any judgment passed by any Court  "},
{ "id" : 400, "question" : "The framers of Constitution borrowed the idea of Judicial Review from Constitution of ", "answer" : " - USA   "},
{ "id" : 401, "question" : "The framers of Constitution adopted the doctrine of Judicial Review ", "answer" : "  to ensure  proper working of the federal system of the government  "},
{ "id" : 402, "question" : "It became imperative for the framers of the Indian Constitution to adopt the doctrine of  Judicial Review because of ", "answer" : " Adoption of Federal system of Government  "},
{ "id" : 403, "question" : "Which Amendment curtailed the Supreme Court/High Court’s power of Judicial Review?  ", "answer" : "  42nd   "},
{ "id" : 404, "question" : "The concept of ‘Judicial Activism’ gained currency in India in ", "answer" : " 1990s  "},
{ "id" : 405, "question" : "Judicial Activism has led to increase in the powers of ", "answer" : " Judiciary   "},
{ "id" : 406, "question" : "The concept of Judicial Review is borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " USA  "},
{ "id" : 407, "question" : "In India, power of Judicial Review is restricted because ", "answer" : " Constitution is supreme  "},
{ "id" : 408, "question" : "While imparting justice, the Supreme Court relies on the principle of ", "answer" : " Procedure  established by law   "},
{ "id" : 409, "question" : "On which List does the Union Government enjoy exclusive powers? ", "answer" : "  Union List  "},
{ "id" : 410, "question" : "On which List do the States enjoy exclusive jurisdiction? ", "answer" : "  State List   "},
{ "id" : 411, "question" : "The subjects of National Importance were enumerated under ", "answer" : " Union List   "},
{ "id" : 412, "question" : "Subjects like Defence and External Affairs are enumerated under ", "answer" : " List I   "},
{ "id" : 413, "question" : "Subjects of Local Importance were enumerated under ", "answer" : " List II   "},
{ "id" : 414, "question" : "The Constitution of India vests the Residuary powers in ", "answer" : " Union Government   "},
{ "id" : 415, "question" : "Under the Constitution, Residuary Powers vested with the ", "answer" : " Union Government  "},
{ "id" : 416, "question" : "In case of conflict between the Central and State laws on a subject in Concurrent List ", "answer" : "  Law of the Center prevails   "},
{ "id" : 417, "question" : "The concept of Concurrent List is borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " Australia   "},
{ "id" : 418, "question" : "At the time of accession to the Dominion, the States acceded only three subjects: ", "answer" : "  Defence, Foreign Affairs and Communication  "},
{ "id" : 419, "question" : "The Constitution of India has created ", "answer" : " very strong center  "},
{ "id" : 420, "question" : "The Parliament can legislate on any subject in the state list ", "answer" : " in all these cases  "},
{ "id" : 421, "question" : "The Central Government can issue directions to the State with regard to the subjects in ", "answer" : "  All these Lists  "},
{ "id" : 422, "question" : "Which among the following subject is transferred from State List to Concurrent List by  42nd Constitutional Amendment? ", "answer" : " Education   "},
{ "id" : 423, "question" : "A Law passed by the State Legislature on a Concurrent list gets precedence over the  Central Law if ", "answer" : " It was approved for the President  "},
{ "id" : 424, "question" : "Water disputes between the States shall be decided by", "answer" : " A Body appointed by  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 425, "question" : "A tax shall not be levied or collected except by the authority of the ", "answer" : "  Law   "},
{ "id" : 426, "question" : "The main purpose to impose taxes is to ", "answer" : "  Run the machinery of State   "},
{ "id" : 427, "question" : "The Provisions regarding division of taxes between Union and State can be suspended ", "answer" : "  During National Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 428, "question" : "The procedure for amendment of the Indian Constitution is ", "answer" : "  partly rigid and  flexible   "},
{ "id" : 429, "question" : "The Amendment procedure of the Constitution of India has been modeled on the  Constitutional pattern of ", "answer" : " South Africa  "},
{ "id" : 430, "question" : "Which Article of the Indian Constitution deals with the amendment procedure? ", "answer" : "  368   "},
{ "id" : 431, "question" : "Which was the lengthiest Amendment to the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  42nd   "},
{ "id" : 432, "question" : "Which Amendment affirmed the right of the Lok Sabha to amend any part of the  Constitution? ", "answer" : " 24th   "},
{ "id" : 433, "question" : "The 24th Amendment became necessary as a result of the Supreme Court judgment in ", "answer" : " - Golak Nath Case   "},
{ "id" : 434, "question" : "After a Bill is passed by the Parliament it is sent to the President for his assent, who can  return it for reconsideration to Lok Sabha. But if the Bill is re-passed and sent to the President for  his assent, he ", "answer" : "  has to sign it  "},
{ "id" : 435, "question" : "If Finance Minister fails to get Annual Budget passed in the Lok Sabha, the Prime  Minister can ", "answer" : "  submit resignation of his Cabinet  "},
{ "id" : 436, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General acts as the ", "answer" : " Guardian of public finances  "},
{ "id" : 437, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General is appointed by ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 438, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General holds Office ", "answer" : " for a term of six years  "},
{ "id" : 439, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General can be removed from his Office before the expiry  of his term by the ", "answer" : "President on the recommendation of the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 440, "question" : "The salary and allowances of the Comptroller and Auditor General are paid out of the ", "answer" : "  Consolidated Fund of India  "},
{ "id" : 441, "question" : "The salary and allowances of the Comptroller and Auditor General ", "answer" : "  are determined  by the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 442, "question" : "The Constitution secures the independence of the Comptroller and Auditor General by ", "answer" : "  (i) making the removal of CAG very difficult, (ii) providing that his salary and service  conditions shall not be changed to his disadvantage & (iii) by giving the CAG complete  control over his administrative staff  "},
{ "id" : 443, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General performs ", "answer" : " only audit functions  "},
{ "id" : 444, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General submits his annual report regarding the Center to  the ", "answer" : "President  "},
{ "id" : 445, "question" : "The Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India was created ", "answer" : " under the  Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 446, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General is intimately connected with the following  Committee of the Parliament? ", "answer" : "  Public Accounts Committee   "},
{ "id" : 447, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General presents a detailed review of Union Accounts to the  Union Finance Minister every ", "answer" : " twelve months  "},
{ "id" : 448, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General does not audit the accounts of ", "answer" : " Municipal  Bodies  "},
{ "id" : 449, "question" : "The Comptroller and Auditor General has to submit the Audit Report of the Central and  State Governments before the ", "answer" : "  President and Governor   "},
{ "id" : 450, "question" : "Which one of the following is the most important item of expenditure of the Government  of India on the revenue account? ", "answer" : " Interest payments  "},
{ "id" : 451, "question" : "The Attorney General of India is the ", "answer" : "  Highest Legal Officer of Union  Government  "},
{ "id" : 452, "question" : "The Attorney General of India is appointed by the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 453, "question" : "The Attorney General of India holds Office ", "answer" : " during the pleasure of the President  "},
{ "id" : 454, "question" : "Which of the following duties / functions has been assigned to the Attorney General of  India? ", "answer" : "  to render legal advice to Central Government  "},
{ "id" : 455, "question" : "Who of the following acts as the Chief Legal Advisor to the Government of India? ", "answer" : "   Attorney General  "},
{ "id" : 456, "question" : "If the Attorney General of India wishes to tender his resignation before the expiry of his  term, he has to address his resignation to the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 457, "question" : "Who has the right to participate in proceedings of the Parliament even though he is not a  MP? ", "answer" : "  Attorney General of India   "},
{ "id" : 458, "question" : "The three types of Civil Services envisaged under the Constitution are ", "answer" : "  All India  Services, Central Services and State Services  "},
{ "id" : 459, "question" : "Which one of the following is presided over by a Non-member? ", "answer" : "  Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 460, "question" : "If the Rajya Sabha rejects a Money Bill, but follows ", "answer" : "  The Lok Sabha can sent the  same for Presidential assent  "},
{ "id" : 461, "question" : "Which Article provides for the composition of Finance Commission? ", "answer" : " 280   "},
{ "id" : 462, "question" : "The Finance Commission has a term of _____ years. ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 463, "question" : "The Finance Commission consists of _____ number of Members. ", "answer" : "  5   "},
{ "id" : 464, "question" : "Who appoints the Finance Commission? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 465, "question" : "The Report of Finance Commission shall be laid before the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 466, "question" : "Grants-in-aid of revenue to the state is recommended by ", "answer" : " Finance Commission   "},
{ "id" : 467, "question" : "Who finally approves the draft of Five Year Plans? ", "answer" : " National Development Council  "},
{ "id" : 468, "question" : "For those Union Territories without Legislative Councils of their own, laws are passed by  the ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 469, "question" : "The day-to-day administration of the Union Territory is looked after by the ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 470, "question" : "For Union Territories without legislative assemblies on their own, laws are passed by the - ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 471, "question" : "Which one of the following is the 28th State of the Indian Union? ", "answer" : " Jharkhand  "},
{ "id" : 472, "question" : "Which one of the following was a Union Territory before it was accorded the status of a  full-fledged State?", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 473, "question" : "Which one of the following has been wrongly listed as a Union territory?", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 474, "question" : "Who is the competent to prescribe conditions for acquisition of citizenship? ", "answer" : "   Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 475, "question" : "Which of the following is the Indian Constitution to Parliamentary procedures? ", "answer" : "   Adjournment Motion   "},
{ "id" : 476, "question" : "What is the minimum duration in (years) of stay essential before a person can applyfor  Indian citizenship? ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 477, "question" : "Who has the power to increase the salary and allowances of the President of India? ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 478, "question" : "One-third of the members of the Rajya Sabha retire every ______ year(s). ", "answer" : " two  "},
{ "id" : 479, "question" : "‘Special majority’ means more than ", "answer" : " two-third % majority   "},
{ "id" : 480, "question" : "‘Special leave’ means ", "answer" : " permission granted by the Supreme Court to appeal  "},
{ "id" : 481, "question" : "‘Respite’ means ", "answer" : " awarding lesser punishment  "},
{ "id" : 482, "question" : "‘Violate’ means ", "answer" : "     commit breach of law   "},
{ "id" : 483, "question" : "‘Interpret’ means ", "answer" : "  ascertaining the meaning of a word  "},
{ "id" : 484, "question" : "Which one of the following Commission has not been provided in the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Planning  "},
{ "id" : 485, "question" : "The Planning Commission is a ", "answer" : " Executive Body   "},
{ "id" : 486, "question" : "Which of the following Offices has not been provided in the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Deputy  Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 487, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution provides protection to the Civil Servants? ", "answer" : " 311   "},
{ "id" : 488, "question" : "Who has the power to create All India Services? ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 489, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution authorizes the Parliament to create All India Services? - ", "answer" : " 312  "},
{ "id" : 490, "question" : "Parliament under the Article 312 gets the power to create All India Services when ", "answer" : "   Rajya Sabha passes a Resolution with two-thirds majority  "},
{ "id" : 491, "question" : "Which Article of the Constitution provides for the composition of Public Service  Commission? ", "answer" : " 315  "},
{ "id" : 492, "question" : "The Members of Indian Administrative Services will be under the control of ", "answer" : "   Ministry of Human Resources Development  "},
{ "id" : 493, "question" : "The Members of Indian Police Services will be under the control of ", "answer" : " Home Minister   "},
{ "id" : 494, "question" : "The Members of Indian Forest Services will be under the control of ", "answer" : " Ministry of  Environment and Forest  "},
{ "id" : 495, "question" : "Immediate control of the members of All India Services lies with the ", "answer" : " State  Government  "},
{ "id" : 496, "question" : "The disciplinary actions against the members of All India Services lies with ", "answer" : " Central  Government  "},
{ "id" : 497, "question" : "Members of All India Services hold office during the pleasure of the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 498, "question" : "Which of the following All India Services  contain in the Constitution? ", "answer" : "  (i) All India  Judicial Services, (ii) Indian Forest Services &  (iii) Indian Administrative Services  "},
{ "id" : 499, "question" : "Which of the body which recruits persons to All India Services? ", "answer" : "  Union Public  Service Commission   "},
{ "id" : 500, "question" : "Chairman and Members of UPSC / WBPSCC shall hold Office for a term of __ years and  tenure of __ years.  ", "answer" : "  6/6 and 65/62  "},
{ "id" : 501, "question" : "In the removal of which of the following officials does the Parliament play no role? ", "answer" : "  Chairman of the Union Public Service Commission  "},
{ "id" : 502, "question" : "Chairman and Members of UPSC / WBPSCC may resign their Office by submitting their  resignation to the (OR) Chairman and Members of UPSC / WBPSCC can be removed on ground  of proved misbehavior by the ", "answer" : "President / Governor  "},
{ "id" : 503, "question" : "Salaries and Pension of the Chairman and Members of UPSC shall be charged from the ", "answer" : " Consolidated Fund   "},
{ "id" : 504, "question" : "UPSC / WBPSCC has to submit an Annual Report to the ", "answer" : " Parliament / Governor  "},
{ "id" : 505, "question" : "Who enjoys the Rank of a Cabinet Minister of Indian Union? ", "answer" : " Deputy Chairman of  Planning Commission  "},
{ "id" : 506, "question" : "Planning Commission was composed in the year ", "answer" : " 1950  "},
{ "id" : 507, "question" : "Who heads the National Integration Council? ", "answer" : "PM  "},
{ "id" : 508, "question" : "Recognition of States was done in the year 1956 on the ground of _____ basis. ", "answer" : "  Linguistic   "},
{ "id" : 509, "question" : "Which is the first State in India formed on Linguistic grounds? ", "answer" : "  Andhra Pradesh  "},
{ "id" : 510, "question" : "Which Part of the Constitution incorporates Special provisions to the State of Jammu &  Kashmir? ", "answer" : " XXI   "},
{ "id" : 511, "question" : "The Provisions with regard to the Union Territories are incorporated under the  Constitution by way of ____ Constitution Amendment Act. ", "answer" : "  7th   "},
{ "id" : 512, "question" : "Every Union Territory shall be administered by the ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 513, "question" : "The Union Territory does not have ", "answer" : " Recognized Official language   "},
{ "id" : 514, "question" : "Who has power to create Legislature or Council of Ministers or both for certain Union  Territory (Pondicherry)? ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 515, "question" : "Under Indian Constitution, the Union Territory of Delhi is referred as ", "answer" : "  National  Capital Territory   "},
{ "id" : 516, "question" : "When did Delhi became Union Territory? ", "answer" : "  1956   "},
{ "id" : 517, "question" : "The Administrator appointed under the Article 239 to the Union Territory of Delhi is  called ", "answer" : "Lieutenant Governor  "},
{ "id" : 518, "question" : "Which of the following Union Territory shall have Legislative Assembly? ", "answer" : "  Delhi   "},
{ "id" : 519, "question" : "Legislative Assembly of Delhi shall have power to make laws for the whole of National  Capital Territory with respect to the matter contained in ", "answer" : "  Both List II and III   "},
{ "id" : 520, "question" : "The Chief Minister of Delhi shall be appointed by the ", "answer" : " Lieutenant Governor  "},
{ "id" : 521, "question" : "The Council of Ministers of Delhi shall hold Office during the pleasure of ", "answer" : "  Prime  Minister  "},
{ "id" : 522, "question" : "The Council of Ministers of Delhi shall be collectively responsible to ", "answer" : "  Legislative  Assembly of Delhi   "},
{ "id" : 523, "question" : "The Emergency provision for National Capital Territory of Delhi is enshrined under the  Article ", "answer" : " 239A  "},
{ "id" : 524, "question" : "Who has the power to constitute a High Court to the Union Territory? ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 525, "question" : "Before 1956, the present day Union Territory were characterized as ", "answer" : " Part C States  "},
{ "id" : 526, "question" : "Parliament has delegated some legislative powers in relation to the Union Territory to ", "answer" : "  Union Government   "},
{ "id" : 527, "question" : "The aid and advice rendered by the Council of Ministers to the Administrator of the Union  Territory is ", "answer" : "Discretionary   "},
{ "id" : 528, "question" : "Who is authorized to appoint the Chief Minister of Delhi? ", "answer" : "  Lieutenant Governor  "},
{ "id" : 529, "question" : "In 1954, Government of India introduced decorations (in form of the medals) Bharat  Ratna, Padma Vibhushan, Padma Bhushan, and Padma Sri Awards under the Article ", "answer" : " 18  "},
{ "id" : 530, "question" : "In 1996, the Supreme Court upheld the validity of the Civilians Awards, but  recommended that the total awards to be given each year in all categories should be restricted to ", "answer" : " 50  "},
{ "id" : 531, "question" : "Indian Constitution was inaugurated on ", "answer" : " 26.01.1950   "},
{ "id" : 532, "question" : "The Chairman of Rajya Sabha is ", "answer" : "  Elected by the two Houses of Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 533, "question" : "Which one of the Constitutional posts is enjoyed for a fixed term? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 534, "question" : "Which of the following is not a prescribed qualification to become President of India? ", "answer" : "  Should be a Graduate   "},
{ "id" : 535, "question" : "Which is the highest Court of Justice of India? ", "answer" : "  Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 536, "question" : "The President of India is similar to ", "answer" : " Queen of England   "},
{ "id" : 537, "question" : "President declares emergencies ", "answer" : "  On the advice of the Council of Ministers  "},
{ "id" : 538, "question" : "The President can return a Bill for reconsideration by the Parliament for _____ time(s). ", "answer" : "  One   "},
{ "id" : 539, "question" : "Who was the President of India at Proclamation of Emergency in the year 1976?  ", "answer" : "   Fakhruddin Ali Ahmad  "},
{ "id" : 540, "question" : "Who was the Defence Minister of India during the Indo-China War of 1962? ", "answer" : "  V. K.  Krishna Menon   "},
{ "id" : 541, "question" : "Which portfolio was held by Dr. Rajendra Prasad in Interim Government formed in the  year 1946? ", "answer" : " Food and Agriculture  "},
{ "id" : 542, "question" : "Which system of Government, in which the ‘Real Executive’ is absolutely dependent  upon the wishes of the Legislatures? ", "answer" : "  Parliamentary  "},
{ "id" : 543, "question" : "In India, a tax on agricultural incomes can be levied by ", "answer" : " Only the State  Governments  "},
{ "id" : 544, "question" : "Which one of the following is not among the sources of revenue for the Union? ", "answer" : "   Land revenue  "},
{ "id" : 545, "question" : "Under which Articles, the Supreme Court has been given the powers to review any  judgment pronounced or order made it previously? ", "answer" : " 137  "},
{ "id" : 546, "question" : "The office of the Lokpal and Lokayuktha in India is based on one of the following? ", "answer" : "  Ombudsman in Scandinavia   "},
{ "id" : 547, "question" : "The constituents of Indian Parliament, as mentioned in the Constitution are the ", "answer" : "  President, Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 548, "question" : "The name of Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands was changed to Lakshadweep by  an Act of Parliament in ", "answer" : " 1973  "},
{ "id" : 549, "question" : "The full status of ‘State’ was conferred upon the Union Territories of Manipur and Tripura  in ", "answer" : " 1972  "},
{ "id" : 550, "question" : "Which one of the following States / Union Territories of the country has more than 50%  tribal population of the total population? ", "answer" : " Dadra and Nagar Haveli   "},
{ "id" : 551, "question" : "The Residuary Powers (i.e. those relating to subjects not mentioned in any of the three  lists included in the VII Schedule) are, according to our Constitution, vested in the ", "answer" : " Union  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 552, "question" : "The Secretary-General of Lok Sabha, who is the Chief of its Secretariat, is ", "answer" : "   Appointed by the Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 553, "question" : "Which Commission was set up in pursuance of a definite provision under the Article of  the Indian Constitution? ", "answer" : "  Election  "},
{ "id" : 554, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a type of relationship specified by the Constitution of  India between Center and States? ", "answer" : "  Judicial  "},
{ "id" : 555, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a constitutionally mandated body? ", "answer" : "  Center-State  relations   "},
{ "id" : 556, "question" : "Who was the first Chairman of the Planning Commission? ", "answer" : "  Jawaharlal Nehru   "},
{ "id" : 557, "question" : "Who among the following enjoy the rank of a Cabinet Minister? ", "answer" : " (i) Deputy  Chairman of Planning Commission, (ii) Leader of Opposition in Lok Sabha & (iii) Speaker  of Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 558, "question" : "Which is the constitutional authority that has been made responsible for constituting the  Finance Commission periodically? ", "answer" : "  President of India  "},
{ "id" : 559, "question" : "The Finance Commission is normally expected to be constituted after every ____ years. ", "answer" : "  Five  "},
{ "id" : 560, "question" : "Which is true for the Finance Commission?  ", "answer" : "  It is constituted under the Article  280 of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 561, "question" : "Who among the following was the Chairman of the Committee on Pricing and Taxation  of Petroleum products? ", "answer" : "  Dr. C. Rangarajan   "},
{ "id" : 562, "question" : "Who among the following was the Head of the Investment Commission which submitted  its Report to the Government of India recently (2007)? ", "answer" : "  Ratan Tata  "},
{ "id" : 563, "question" : "Who was the Chief Justice of India when Public Interest Litigation was introduced to the  Indian Judicial system? ", "answer" : "  P. N. Bhagwati  "},
{ "id" : 564, "question" : "The concept of Public Interest Litigation has strengthened ", "answer" : "  Rule of Law  "},
{ "id" : 565, "question" : "Public Interest Litigation means ", "answer" : "  Petitions by any conscious person or  organization on behalf of an aggrieved person or group for reasons of interest of the public  "},
{ "id" : 566, "question" : "In India, National Income is estimated by ", "answer" : " Central Statistical Organization  "},
{ "id" : 567, "question" : "As per Article 100 (3), the quorum to constitute a meeting of either House of Parliament is  ", "answer" : " One-tenth of the total number of members of that House  "},
{ "id" : 568, "question" : "The ‘Rule of Law’ means ", "answer" : "  That no person can be punished unless his guilt is  established by a fair trial  "},
{ "id" : 569, "question" : "The term ‘Law’ used in the expression ‘Rule of Law’ refers to ", "answer" : "  Positive Law  "},
{ "id" : 570, "question" : "The draft of the Indian Penal Code was prepared by _____ Indian Law Commission. ", "answer" : " -  First  "},
{ "id" : 571, "question" : "In a particular case, the advice tendered by the Council of Ministers is sent back by the  President for reconsideration. If the Council of Ministers adhere to their earlier advice, the  President ", "answer" : "  Has no option but to accept such advice  "},
{ "id" : 572, "question" : "In which of the following situations can the President promulgate the Ordinance? ", "answer" : "   Parliament is not in session  "},
{ "id" : 573, "question" : "The gap (period) between two sessions of the Lok Sabha is termed as ", "answer" : " Prorogation   "},
{ "id" : 574, "question" : "Both the Union and the States derive their authority from the Constitution of India which  divides, as between them, all of the following powers, except ", "answer" : "  Judicial  "},
{ "id" : 575, "question" : "Which of the following Schedules in the Constitution divides the legislative powers  between the Union and the States? ", "answer" : "  VII  "},
{ "id" : 576, "question" : "The powers to legislate with respect to any matter not enumerated in any of the three Lists  are mentioned as Residuary Powers. Which of the following is empowered to determine finally as  to whether or not a particular matters falls in this category? ", "answer" : "  Judiciary only   "},
{ "id" : 577, "question" : "The vesting of Residuary Powers under our Constitution in the Union, instead of the State  Legislatures, follows the precedent of the __________ Constitution. ", "answer" : "  Canadian  "},
{ "id" : 578, "question" : "When two Houses of Parliament differ regarding a Bill, then the deadlock is resolved by ", "answer" : "  A Joint Sitting of the two Houses  "},
{ "id" : 579, "question" : "‘Closure’ in Parliamentary terminology means ", "answer" : "  A rule of legislative procedure  under which further debate on a motion can be stopped  "},
{ "id" : 580, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is not correct? ", "answer" : "  The proposal for  amending the Constitution can only be initiated in Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 581, "question" : "In which of the following cases is a joint session of the two Houses of Parliament not  necessary? ", "answer" : "  A Bill to amend the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 582, "question" : "Which of the following is not a tool of legislative control over administration in India? ", "answer" : "   Dissolution of House  "},
{ "id" : 583, "question" : "The Secretary General of the Lok Sabha is the Chief of its Secretariat and is ", "answer" : "  Appointed by the Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 584, "question" : "Main Standing Committee of Lok Sabha is / are ", "answer" : "  Public Accounts,  Public  Understanding,  Estimate   "},
{ "id" : 585, "question" : "To whom does the Public Accounts Committee submits its report? ", "answer" : "  Speaker of Lok  Sabha   "},
{ "id" : 586, "question" : "The work of General Purpose Committee is to advice the ", "answer" : " Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 587, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a Parliamentary Committee? ", "answer" : " Demands for Grants  Committee   "},
{ "id" : 588, "question" : "Which of the following Committees are sometimes described as ‘Twin Sisters’? ", "answer" : "   Public Account and Estimate Committees  "},
{ "id" : 589, "question" : "To which of the following Bills the President must accord his sanction without sending it  back for fresh consideration? ", "answer" : "  Money Bill  "},
{ "id" : 590, "question" : "All of the following statements in regard to Money Bills are incorrect, except ", "answer" : "  A  Money Bill can only be introduced in Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha has no power to make a  change in it against the will of Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 591, "question" : "14 days notice is necessary for moving a ", "answer" : " Resolution of impeaching the President  "},
{ "id" : 592, "question" : "In the Union Budget in India, which Expenditure is the largest in amount? ", "answer" : "  Non-Plan   "},
{ "id" : 593, "question" : "The 11th Five-Year Plan has been named as ", "answer" : " Towards Infrastructural and  Agricultural Growth  "},
{ "id" : 594, "question" : "On which of the following subjects does the power to legislate vest both in the Union as  well as the State legislatures? ", "answer" : "  Acquisition and requisitioning of property  "},
{ "id" : 595, "question" : "The President is empowered to establish an Inter-State Council if at any time it appears to  him that the public interests would be served thereby. Which of the following has not so been set  up? ", "answer" : "  Inter-State Commerce Council  "},
{ "id" : 596, "question" : "The Council of Ministers in India remains in their Office till it enjoys the support of ", "answer" : "   Majority of the Members of Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 597, "question" : "The Council of Ministers is ", "answer" : " Larger than Cabinet   "},
{ "id" : 598, "question" : "The resolution for removing the Vice President of India can be moved in the ", "answer" : "  Rajya  Sabha alone  "},
{ "id" : 599, "question" : "Anti-Defection Act relating to disqualification of Members of Parliament and State  Legislatures does not covers ", "answer" : " Chairman of Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 600, "question" : "Which statement is not correct? ", "answer" : "  The Supreme Court of India has to look into all  disputes with regard to the election of Vice President of India  "},
{ "id" : 601, "question" : "Which one of the following Amendments to the Constitution clearly has laid down that  the President of India is bound to accept the advice given by the Council of Ministers? ", "answer" : "  42nd  "},
{ "id" : 602, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is not correct? ", "answer" : "  North-East India accounts  for a little over half of the country’s tribal population  "},
{ "id" : 603, "question" : "Under which Ministry of the Government of India does the Food and Nutrition Board  work? ", "answer" : "  Ministry of Human Resource Development  "},
{ "id" : 604, "question" : "The Archaeological Survey of India is an attached office of the Department / Ministry of - ", "answer" : "  Culture  "},
{ "id" : 605, "question" : "Survey of India is under the Ministry of ", "answer" : " Science and Technology  "},
{ "id" : 606, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a Department in Ministry of Human Resources  Development? ", "answer" : "Technical Education and Literacy  "},
{ "id" : 607, "question" : "Which one of the following Articles of the Constitution of India says that the executive  power of every State shall be so exercised as not to impeded or prejudice the exercise of the  executive power of the Union? ", "answer" : " 257   "},
{ "id" : 608, "question" : "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution did the President give his assent to the  ordinance on electoral reforms when it was sent back to him by the Union Cabinet without making  any changes (in the year 2002)? ", "answer" : " 123  "},
{ "id" : 609, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is correct? ", "answer" : "  There is no constitutional bar  for a nominated member to be appointed as a Union Minister  "},
{ "id" : 610, "question" : "The power to enlarge the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court of India with respect to any  matter included in the Union List of Legislative Powers rests with  ", "answer" : " Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 611, "question" : "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution did the President make a reference to the  Supreme Court to seek the Court’s opinion on the Constitutional validity of the Election  Commission’s decision on deferring the Gujarat Assembly elections (in the year 2002)? ", "answer" : "   143  "},
{ "id" : 612, "question" : "Which one of the following statements is not correct? ", "answer" : "Among all the States of  India, Maharashtra publishes the largest number of newspapers  "},
{ "id" : 613, "question" : "With reference to the Indian Polity, which one of the following statements is correct? ", "answer" : "   President can make the ordinance only when either of the two Houses of Parliament is not in  session  "},
{ "id" : 614, "question" : "The Consultative Committee of the Members of Parliament for Railway Zones is  constituted by ", "answer" : " Ministry of Parliamentary Affairs   "},
{ "id" : 615, "question" : "The Supreme Court of India tenders advice to the President of India on the matter of law  or fact ", "answer" : "  Only if he seeks such advice  "},
{ "id" : 616, "question" : "Which is correct under the hierarchy of Courts? ", "answer" : "  Supreme Court, High Courts,  Other Courts  "},
{ "id" : 617, "question" : "‘Judicial Activism’ refers to ", "answer" : " Expansion of jurisdiction of courts   "},
{ "id" : 618, "question" : "Which one of the following duty is not performed by the Comptroller and Auditor General  of India? ", "answer" : " To control the receipt and issue of public money, and to ensure that the public  revenue is lodged in the exchequer  "},
{ "id" : 619, "question" : "If a new State of Indian Union is to be created, which Schedule of Constitution must be  amended? ", "answer" : " First  "},
{ "id" : 620, "question" : "Which subject is under the Union List in the 7th Schedule of the Constitution of India? ", "answer" : "  Regulation of labor   "},
{ "id" : 621, "question" : "The Speaker can ask a member of the House to stop speaking and let another member  speak. This phenomenon is known as ", "answer" : " Yielding the floor  "},
{ "id" : 622, "question" : "The sovereign power under the Indian Constitution rests with the ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 623, "question" : "Parliament is an instrument of _____ Justice. ", "answer" : "  Legal  "},
{ "id" : 624, "question" : "Under which Article of the Constitution does the Central Government gives Plan  assistance to the State Government? ", "answer" : "  275   "},
{ "id" : 625, "question" : "Which one of the following is the correct sequence of Union Territories of India in the  increasing order of their area? ", "answer" : "  Lakshadweep – Chandigarh – Pondicherry – Andaman  and Nicobar Islands  "},
{ "id" : 626, "question" : "What is Value Added Tax? ", "answer" : "  A simple, transparent, easy to pay tax imposed on the  consumers  "},
{ "id" : 627, "question" : "The VAT adopted by 21 States replaced which of the following taxes? ", "answer" : "  State Sales  Tax   "},
{ "id" : 628, "question" : "Which one of the following is not a Central Government Tax? ", "answer" : "  Land Tax  "},
{ "id" : 629, "question" : "Who is the President of the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research? ", "answer" : "  Prime  Minister  "},
{ "id" : 631, "question" : "Under the Constitution, which of the following functionaries can be suspended? ", "answer" : "   Members of Public Service Commission  "},
{ "id" : 632, "question" : "In India, present trend of rapid urbanization is due to ", "answer" : " Lack of employment  opportunities in rural areas  "},
{ "id" : 633, "question" : "Under the Indian Parliamentary practices, normally how many sessions take place? ", "answer" : "  3  "},
{ "id" : 634, "question" : "The Contingency Fund of India rests at the disposal of the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 635, "question" : "Which is not a characteristic of economically under developed countries? ", "answer" : "  High  proportion of labor in secondary activity  "},
{ "id" : 636, "question" : "Who declares war and concludes peace? ", "answer" : "  President, in the advice of the  Cabinet                         VI. STATE GOVERNMENT  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "Who appoints the Governor of the State? ", "answer" : "  The President  "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "Membership of Legislative Assembly can vary between ", "answer" : "  60 - 500   "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "What is the minimum age in years for becoming the MLC and MLA in the State? ", "answer" : "  30  and 25   "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "What is the tenure in years of Office of MLA and MLC in the State? ", "answer" : "  5 and 6   "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "What is the eligibility age and tenure of Office of the Governor? (in years) ", "answer" : "  35 and 5   "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "The State Legislature unless dissolved earlier shall continue for a period of ______years. ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "The Legislative Council shall not be subjected to dissolution however one-third of its  members shall retire after every _____ years. ", "answer" : " 2  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "Who appoints the Vice Chancellors of the Universities? ", "answer" : "  Governor  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "Who is the Executive (Constitutional) Head of the State Government? ", "answer" : "  Governor   "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "The Executive powers of the State Government shall be exercised in the name of ", "answer" : "   Governor   "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "Generally, the Governor belongs to ", "answer" : " some other State  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "The Governor of a State acts as ", "answer" : "  Agent of President  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "The Governor of the State shall be appointed by the ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "The Governor holds Office ", "answer" : "  during the pleasure of the President  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "As a matter of convention, while appointing the Governor of a State, the President consults  ", "answer" : "  State Chief Minister   "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "The Governor is the part and parcel of the ", "answer" : " State Legislature   "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "The salary and allowances of the Governor are charged to ", "answer" : "  The Consolidated Fund  of the State   "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "The emoluments of the Ministers in the State Government are determined by ", "answer" : "  Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "The salaries and allowances of the Speaker of Legislative Assembly and Chairman of  Legislative Council shall be determined by the ", "answer" : "   State Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "The emoluments, allowances and privileges of the Governor shall be determined by the ", "answer" : " - Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "If the Governor of a State wishes to relinquish Office before the expiry of his / her term, he  / she has to address resignation ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "The Governor plays a dual role as an agent of the President and as the ", "answer" : "   Constitutional Head of the State  "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "The Governor of a State should ", "answer" : "  not hold any other office of profit  "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "The Governor may resign his / her Office by writing to the ", "answer" : " President   "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "Can one person act as Governor of more than one State? ", "answer" : "  Yes  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "When a person acts as Governor of more than one State, his / her salary is ", "answer" : "  shared  by the concerned States  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "Which one of the following legislative powers is enjoyed by the Governor? ", "answer" : " (i) can  nominate certain members of Anglo-Indian community to the Legislative Assembly, (ii) can  summon or prorogue the State Legislative, (iii) can appoint one-sixth the members of the  Legislative Council  "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "Who discharges the duties of the Office of Governor if it falls vacant due to death or  resignation? ", "answer" : "  Chief Justice of High Court  "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "The Governor of a State is administered the oath of Office by (OR) The Governor before  entering upon his Office has to administer his oath before the ", "answer" : " Chief Justice of High  Court   "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "There is no provision for the impeachment of the ", "answer" : " Governor  "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "Which one of the following is correct regarding the Governor of a State? ", "answer" : " (i) No  Money Bill can be introduced in State Legislature without prior permission of Governor, (ii)  He can recommend to the President to impose President’s Rule in the State, (iii) He has the  power to issue ordinances when the legislature is not in session  "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "The Governor can issue ordinances ", "answer" : " only during the recess of the State  Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "The ordinances issued by the Governor are subject to approval by the ", "answer" : " State  Legislature   "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "A Governor ", "answer" : "  may be transferred from one State to another State  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "The Governor has power to dissolve ", "answer" : " Legislative Assembly   "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Who appoints and administers the oath for the Chief Minister and Council of Ministers? ", "answer" : "  Governor  "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "The Contingency Fund of the State is operated by the ", "answer" : "Governor  "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "The Governor is accountable for his / her actions to the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "Unless approved by the State Legislature, the ordinance issued by the Governor remains in  force for a maximum period of ", "answer" : " six months  "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "A Legislative Bill which did not receive the Governor’s immediate assent was ", "answer" : "   Jammu & Kashmir citizenship   "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "The District Judges and Magistrate of the Civil Courts shall be appointed by the ", "answer" : "  Governor   "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "The High Court of Karnataka established in the year ", "answer" : " 1884  "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "The Guwahati High Court has territorial jurisdiction over ___ number of States. ", "answer" : " 4  "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "Which High Court has four Principal Benches? ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "The High Court for the territory of Andaman and Nicobar is the High Court of ", "answer" : " West  Bengal   "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "The number of States under the Jurisdiction of a High Court shall be decided on the basis  of ", "answer" : "  Area and Population   "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "Who decides the number of Judges in the High Court? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "High Courts in India were first started (1862) at ", "answer" : "  Bombay, Calcutta and Madras   "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "The Governor can recommend imposition of President’s Rule in the State ", "answer" : "  At his  discretion  "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "The term of Legislative Assembly can be extended for a period of ____ during the time of  Emergency. ", "answer" : " One year   "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "Governor will act under the following circumstance with advice of Ministers while  returning ", "answer" : "  Appointing the Advocate General   "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "Parliament or State Legislature can declare a seat vacant if the member is absent from the  session for a period of _____ days without permission. ", "answer" : " 60  "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "‘Bicameral’ means", "answer" : "  Presence of two Houses in the State   "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "‘Unicameral’ means ", "answer" : "  Presence of one House in the State   "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "What is the system of Legislature in the State of Karnataka? ", "answer" : "  Bicameral   "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "Which State(s) is / are having Bicameral system?", "answer" : "Uttar Pradesh, Karnataka ,  Maharashtra,   "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "Which State(s) is / are having Unicameral system?", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "Which are the two States having common Capital? ", "answer" : "  Punjab and Haryana   "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "Sikkim was admitted as a full-fledged State of Indian Union in the year _____. ", "answer" : "   1975   "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "The Residuary power with respect to the Jammu & Kashmir rest with the ", "answer" : "  State  Government of Jammu & Kashmir   "},
{ "id" : 61, "question" : "Who appoints the Governor of Jammu & Kashmir? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "Which of the following bodies can be abolished but not dissolved? ", "answer" : " State Legislative  Council  "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "Who appoints the Chief Minister and Council of Ministers in the State? ", "answer" : "  Governor  "},
{ "id" : 64, "question" : "Who appoints the Chief Justice and other Judges of the High Court? ", "answer" : "  President   "},
{ "id" : 65, "question" : "What is the retirement age in years for Chief Justice and other Judges of High Court? ", "answer" : "   62   "},
{ "id" : 66, "question" : "Salaries and other emoluments of the High Court Judges shall be determined by the ", "answer" : "  Parliament   "},
{ "id" : 67, "question" : "Which among the following Article of the Constitution empowers the High Court to issue  writs of various kinds? ", "answer" : "  226  "},
{ "id" : 68, "question" : "Writ Jurisdiction of the Supreme Court under Article 32 is not wider than that of the Writ  Jurisdiction of the High Court under Article 226 because the High Court may exercise this power  in relation to ", "answer" : "  Violation of Fundamental and Legal Rights  "},
{ "id" : 69, "question" : "Article 227 of the Indian Constitution deals with the ", "answer" : "  High Court’s power of  superintendence over all Courts and Tribunals within its Jurisdiction  "},
{ "id" : 70, "question" : "Who has power to establish common High Court for two or more States and Union  Territories? ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 71, "question" : "In WB, the number of seats in Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council are", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 72, "question" : "Who is having power to remove the Governor before expiry of the tenure? ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 73, "question" : "What is the retirement age in years of a High Court Judge? ", "answer" : " 62  "},
{ "id" : 74, "question" : "The total members in the Legislative Council should not be less than (Article 171). ", "answer" : "   40   "},
{ "id" : 75, "question" : "The Legislative Council is a permanent House, however, _____ number of members retire  after every ____ years. ", "answer" : "  One-third and 2   "},
{ "id" : 76, "question" : "A Cabinet Minister of a State Government can be removed by the ", "answer" : " Chief Minister  "},
{ "id" : 77, "question" : "The Council of Ministers in the State remains in power for  ", "answer" : "  as long as it retains  the confidence of Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 78, "question" : "The State Council of Ministers has to tender their resignation if vote of no-confidence is  passed against it by the ", "answer" : " Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 79, "question" : "Who is the Channel of Communication between the Governor and the State Council of  Ministers? ", "answer" : "    Chief Minister  "},
{ "id" : 80, "question" : "Chief Minister of all the States are the Members of ", "answer" : " National Development  Council   "},
{ "id" : 81, "question" : "This is not the power of the Chief Minister. ", "answer" : "  Control over State Judiciary  "},
{ "id" : 82, "question" : "The Chief Minister of a State cannot take part in the election of President if he is ", "answer" : "  A  member of the Legislative Council of the State  "},
{ "id" : 83, "question" : "If a member of Lok Sabha is appointed as the Chief Minister of a State ", "answer" : "  He must  become a member of the State Legislature within six months  "},
{ "id" : 84, "question" : "What is the effect of the resignation or death of the Chief Minister of the State? ", "answer" : "   Dissolves the Legislative Assembly   "},
{ "id" : 85, "question" : "Which tax is levied by the Union and collected and appropriated by the States? ", "answer" : "   Stamp duties   "},
{ "id" : 86, "question" : "Which category of professional people are entitled to elect their representatives to the State  Legislative Council? ", "answer" : " Teachers of not lower than secondary school level in the State  "},
{ "id" : 87, "question" : "The Graduates constitute a separate constituency for the election of the specified number of  members to ", "answer" : " State Legislative Council   "},
{ "id" : 88, "question" : "Legislative Council is ", "answer" : "  not dissolved   "},
{ "id" : 89, "question" : "How many States in India have Legislative Councils? ", "answer" : " 5  "},
{ "id" : 90, "question" : "Which among the following House cannot be dissolved but can be abolished?", "answer" : "    Legislative Council  "},
{ "id" : 91, "question" : "Without certificate of High Court, an appeal can made to Supreme Court ", "answer" : "  with the  special leave of Supreme Court  "},
{ "id" : 92, "question" : "What is meant by ‘Court of Records’? ", "answer" : "  The court that preserves all the records  "},
{ "id" : 93, "question" : "The Legislative Council in a State can be created or disbanded by the ", "answer" : " Parliament  on the recommendation of the State Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 94, "question" : "The Members of the State Legislature can claim immunity from _____ Proceedings. ", "answer" : "  Civil  "},
{ "id" : 95, "question" : "The major part of following central revenues goes to various State Governments in India ", "answer" : "  Excise Duty  "},
{ "id" : 96, "question" : "Which of the following is the most important source of revenue of the states in India? ", "answer" : "  Sales Tax  "},
{ "id" : 97, "question" : "Who Superintendents all subordinate courts in a State? ", "answer" : "  High Court   "},
{ "id" : 98, "question" : "Which one of the following High Courts has the territorial jurisdiction over Andaman and  Nicobar Islands? ", "answer" : "  Calcutta  "},
{ "id" : 99, "question" : "Power to extend or restrict the Jurisdiction of High Court vest with ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 100, "question" : "A temporary Judge of High Court can hold Office for a maximum period of ", "answer" : "   Two years   "},
{ "id" : 101, "question" : "Which one of the following Union Territories has a High Court of its own? ", "answer" : "  Delhi   "},
{ "id" : 102, "question" : "When there is no majority party in the State Legislative Assembly, the main consideration  governing the appointment of a Chief Minister by Governor is the ", "answer" : "  ability of the person  who is most likely to command a stable majority  "},
{ "id" : 103, "question" : "If there is a dispute between two States ", "answer" : " only Supreme Court has jurisdiction to  decide that case  "},
{ "id" : 104, "question" : "Which of the following States are involved in disputes over sharing of river waters?", "answer" : "  (i) Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat , (ii) Andhra Pradesh and Karnataka, (iii) Karnataka and  Tamil Nadu   "},
{ "id" : 105, "question" : "Constitution empowers State Governments to make special law for ", "answer" : " Women and  Children   "},
{ "id" : 106, "question" : "The State Government does not enjoy any control over local bodies with regard to ", "answer" : " Personal matters  "},
{ "id" : 107, "question" : "The Speaker of the Legislative Assembly shall be elected by the ", "answer" : " Members of  Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 108, "question" : "The Speaker of Legislative Assembly can vacate his Office by addressing his resignation  to the ", "answer" : "Deputy Speaker of Legislative Assembly   "},
{ "id" : 109, "question" : "Find out the correct response: ‘After the State Legislature is dissolved the Speaker of  Legislative Assembly’? ", "answer" : "  Remains as Speaker until the 1st Meeting of the Legislative  Assembly after the dissolution  "},
{ "id" : 110, "question" : "The Speaker of the Legislative Assembly shall be removed by the House by passing a  resolution ", "answer" : " after 14 days clear notice passed by majority of all the Members of the  House  "},
{ "id" : 111, "question" : "Who among the following is described as the Custodian of State Legislative Assembly? ", "answer" : "  Speaker  "},
{ "id" : 112, "question" : "Who is the neutral in the affairs of the party politics? ", "answer" : "  Speaker of Legislative  Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 113, "question" : "The Speaker of Legislative Assembly enjoys ", "answer" : "  Right to vote only in case of tie   "},
{ "id" : 114, "question" : "What is the minimum gap permissible between the two sessions of the Legislature? ", "answer" : "   Six months   "},
{ "id" : 115, "question" : "The authority to allot the agenda of the State Legislative Assembly is ", "answer" : " Speaker of  Legislative Assembly  "},
{ "id" : 116, "question" : "Find out the correct response to the Ordinance promulgated by the Governor? ", "answer" : "  has  the same force as the law made by the State Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 117, "question" : "What shall be the qualification of a person to be appointed as the Advocate General for  the State? ", "answer" : " Qualified to be appointed as Judge of High Court  "},
{ "id" : 118, "question" : "The Governor does not appoint ", "answer" : " Judges of High Court  "},
{ "id" : 119, "question" : "An Advocate General shall hold Office during the pleasure of the ", "answer" : " Governor  "},
{ "id" : 120, "question" : "Who has the power to create and abolish Legislative Council if the Legislative Assembly  of State passes a resolution to that effect? ", "answer" : "  Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 121, "question" : "Which of the following taxes is levied by the State Government only? ", "answer" : "  Entertainment Tax   "},
{ "id" : 122, "question" : "Goa got the status of Statehood by the way of _____ Constitutional Amendment. ", "answer" : "  56th  "},
{ "id" : 123, "question" : "Law with regard to Anti-defection is inserted by way of ____ Constitutional Amendment.  ", "answer" : "  52nd   "},
{ "id" : 124, "question" : "Among the following Amendments, which is considered as Mini-Constitution? ", "answer" : "  42nd   "},
{ "id" : 125, "question" : "73rd and 74th Constitutional Amendments is pertaining to ", "answer" : " Local Self Government  "},
{ "id" : 126, "question" : "State Emergency (President’s Rule) can be declared ", "answer" : "  When the Government  of the State cannot be carried in accordance with the Provision of the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 127, "question" : "Which Article gives Special Provisions to the State of Jammu & Kashmir? ", "answer" : " 370  "},
{ "id" : 128, "question" : "The President can make a Proclamation of Emergency in Jammu & Kashmir with the ", "answer" : " Concurrence of the State Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 129, "question" : "There is no provision in the Constitution for the impeachment of ", "answer" : " Governor  "},
{ "id" : 130, "question" : "The member of State Public Service Commission can be removed on the ground of  misbehavior only after an enquiry has been conducted by the ", "answer" : " High Court of the State  "},
{ "id" : 131, "question" : "Who can recommend abolition or creation of the Legislative Council in a State? ", "answer" : "  Legislative Assembly of the State  "},
{ "id" : 132, "question" : "Where were the High Courts in India first set up? ", "answer" : "  Bombay, Madras and  Calcutta   "},
{ "id" : 133, "question" : "The High Courts at Bombay, Calcutta and Madras were established under the ", "answer" : "  Indian High Courts Act,   "},
{ "id" : 134, "question" : "The Additional and Acting Judges of the High Court are appointed by the ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 135, "question" : "High Courts exercise ", "answer" : " Writ Jurisdiction  "},
{ "id" : 136, "question" : "As per Indian Protocol, who among the following ranks highest in the order of  precedence? ", "answer" : "  State Governor   "},
{ "id" : 137, "question" : "The salaries and allowances of the Judges of the High Court are charges to the ", "answer" : "   Consolidated Fund of the State   "},
{ "id" : 138, "question" : "High Courts enjoy ", "answer" : " (i) Original Jurisdiction,  (ii) Administrative powers, (iii)  Appellate Jurisdiction   "},
{ "id" : 139, "question" : "In which area does the State Government not have control over its Local Bodies? ", "answer" : "   Personnel matters   "},
{ "id" : 140, "question" : "Which State Government has decided to provide health insurance to people living below  the poverty line with effective from January 2007? ", "answer" : "  Karnataka  "},
{ "id" : 141, "question" : "What was the scheme to reduce interest burden of the State Government in India through  gradual conversion of high cost debt into low cost debt? ", "answer" : "  Debt-write off Scheme   "},
{ "id" : 142, "question" : "What is the chronological order in which the following States of Indian Union were  created or granted full statehood? ", "answer" : " Andhra Pradesh  >  Maharashtra  >  Nagaland  >  Haryana  "},
{ "id" : 143, "question" : "Which among the following can be transferred by the President which related to High  Court? ", "answer" : "(i) Chief Justice,  (ii) Permanent Judge   "},
{ "id" : 144, "question" : "Which Constitutional Amendment is associated with the linguistic reorganization of a  State? ", "answer" : "  3rd  "},
{ "id" : 145, "question" : "Full Statehood was conferred to Arunachal Pradesh by the ___ Amendment of the  Constitution. ", "answer" : " 55 th                  VII. CONSTITUTIONAL PROVISIONS FOR SCs AND STs, WOMEN, CHILDREN AND OBCs  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "Which Article under the Constitution provides for the reservation of SCs and STs in  the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  300  "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "In which year was ‘untouchability’ abolished in India? ", "answer" : "  1950   "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "The following act does not amount to practicing untouchability ", "answer" : "  denying access to  a home  "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "‘Self-incrimination’ means Compelling a person to ", "answer" : " be a witness against  himself  "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "The Constitution seeks to protect the interests of the SCs and STs by reserving seats for them  in ", "answer" : " public services,  in legislatures   "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "Indian Constitution guarantees reservation to SCs and STs in ", "answer" : " Lok Sabha and  Legislative Assembly   "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "Seats for SCs and STs are not reserved in ", "answer" : "  Rajya Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "The Special Officer who looks into the working of the safeguards for SCs and STs is called  as  ", "answer" : " Commissioner for SCs and STs  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "According to Marriage Act of 1954, the age is fixed at ____ years for men and ____ for  women. ", "answer" : "   21 and 18   "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "The year ____ was declared as the year of women empowerment to the promotion of the  development of women. ", "answer" : "  2001   "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "Who are considered to be the vulnerable group? ", "answer" : "  Women and Children   "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "In which one of the following States is it constitutionally obligatory for the State to have a  separate Minister for Tribal Welfare? ", "answer" : "  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "The reservation for members of SCs and STs has been extended up to ", "answer" : " 2010  "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "Extension of reservation to SCs and STs for another 10 years is provided by way of ____  Constitutional Amendment.  ", "answer" : "  45th   "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "Reservation for the SCs and STs in the Parliament and State Assemblies was extended up  to 2010 by the Amendment ", "answer" : " 79th   "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "Concept of ‘creamy layer’, propounded by Supreme Court with regard to reservations,  refers to ", "answer" : "economically better-off people  "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "What is the maximum percentage of jobs that can be reserved by a State for backward class  people in the government jobs? ", "answer" : "  50%  "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "The Tamil Nadu Reservation Act, which provides for 69% reservation in the jobs and  educational institutional in the State, was placed in the Ninth Schedule by the Amendment ", "answer" : "   76th   "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "Which Article provides for the National Commission of SCs / STs? ", "answer" : "  338 / 338A  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "The National Commission for SCs and STs has to submit an Annual report to the ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "Which Article of the Indian Constitution empowers the President to appoint a Commission  to investigate the conditions of backward classes in general and suggest ameliorative measures? ", "answer" : "  342   "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "Certain seats shall be reserved for the SCs and STs in Lok Sabha on the basis of their ", "answer" : " Population  "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "Minority Groups are recognized on the basis of their ", "answer" : "  Population   "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "Special provisions relating to the Minorities are guaranteed under the Part _____. ", "answer" : "  XVI   "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "Jobs are reserved for SC and ST people ", "answer" : "  both at the time of appointment and  promotion  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "The Mandal Commission for backward classes was set up in ", "answer" : " 1978  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "Which is the Commission appointed by the Government of India to investigate the  conditions of socially and educationally backward classes of the society? ", "answer" : "  Mandal   "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "Which of the following Prime Minister was in favour of implementation of the  recommendation of the Mandal Commission? ", "answer" : " V. P. Singh   "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "Who is empowered to nominate Anglo-Indian Community to Lok Sabha / Legislative  Assembly? ", "answer" : "  President / Governor  "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "How many members will be nominated by President / Governor from Anglo-Indian  Community?  ", "answer" : " 2 / 1  "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "In which one of the following States there is no reservation for the SCs for Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  Jammu & Kashmir   "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Under the Provisions of which Article of the Constitution, the Government abolished the  practice of untouchability? ", "answer" : " 17                  VIII. EMERGENCY PROVISIONS  "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "Emergency Provisions were borrowed from the Constitution of ", "answer" : " Germany   "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "Emergency Provisions under Indian Constitution describes the nature of Indian Polity as ", "answer" : "  Unitary   "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "Which Article under the Constitution authorizes the President to proclaim an emergency? ", "answer" : " 352  "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "Emergency Provisions are enshrined under _____ Part of the Constitution. ", "answer" : "  XVIII   "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "According to the Article 355, it is the duty of the Union to protect States against ", "answer" : "  External Aggression,  Constitutional Breakdown,  Internal Disturbance   "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "The Indian Constitution is designed to work as a Unitary Government during the time of ", "answer" : " - Emergency   "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "When the National Emergency is declared, the following Article is suspended? ", "answer" : " 14  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "While Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the President cannot suspend certain  Fundamental Rights. They are ", "answer" : "  20 and 21  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "The final authority to make a Proclamation of Emergency rests with (OR) _____ is  empowered to declare an Emergency. ", "answer" : "  President  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "President can proclaim an Emergency with the recommendation of the ", "answer" : "  Union  Cabinet   "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "President can proclaim emergency on the recommendation of the Union Cabinet. Such  recommendation shall be ", "answer" : "  Written recommendation  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "How many types of emergencies are envisaged by the Constitution?", "answer" : " 3  "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "Breakdown of Constitutional Machinery in a State is popularly known as ", "answer" : "  President’s Rule   "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "President’s Rule can be imposed on the States ", "answer" : "  on failure of the constitutional  machinery in a State  "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "President’s Rule at the Center is possible ", "answer" : "  during National Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "The President can declare National Emergency ", "answer" : "  On the recommendation of the  Council of Ministers  "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "Proclamation of National Emergency ceases to operate unless approved by the Parliament  within (OR) Once the National Emergency is proclaimed, it should be approved by the Parliament  within (OR) Proclamation issued under Article 352 shall be laid before the Parliament within ", "answer" : " one month  "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "Proclamation issued has been approved by the Parliament will be in force for a period of ", "answer" : " 6  months  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "When the Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, Parliament has power to make laws  for the whole or any part of the territory of India under ", "answer" : "  List II  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "When the Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the Parliament has special powers to  legislate under ", "answer" : " State List   "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "The President can declare National Emergency ", "answer" : "  Due to threat arising on account of  foreign attack or armed rebellion  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "President can proclaim an emergency on the ground of ", "answer" : " External Aggression,  War  , Armed Rebellion   "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "How many times has a National Emergency been declared so far by the President? ", "answer" : "   Thrice   "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "The President can declare Constitutional Emergency in a State ", "answer" : "  If he is satisfied that  a situation has arisen in which the State Government cannot be carried out on in accordance  with the Constitution  "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "Which type of emergency has been declared the maximum number of times? ", "answer" : "   Constitutional Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "Which one of the following types of emergency has not yet declared, till now? ", "answer" : "   Financial Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "A National Emergency can remain in operation with the approval of Parliament for a ", "answer" : "  Indefinite period   "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "This is not a ground to declare National Emergency. ", "answer" : "  serious internal disturbance  "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "To declare National Emergency, a decision must be taken by the ", "answer" : "  Cabinet "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "Financial Emergency can be proclaimed under the Article ____. ", "answer" : " 360 "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "Who is empowered to proclaim the Financial Emergency? ", "answer" : "  President "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Financial Emergency can be proclaimed on the ground of ", "answer" : "  Any part of the Indian Territory is threatened,  Financial stability,  Credit of India  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "The President can declare Financial Emergency ", "answer" : "  If there is a threat to the financial stability or credit of India  "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "During a Financial Emergency, the President ", "answer" : " (i) Order the reduction of salaries of Supreme Court and High Court Judges, (ii) Order the reduction of salaries and  allowances of all Central and State Civil Servants,  (iii) Ask all States to reserve all the  Money or Financial Bills passed by the State Legislature for his consideration  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "When the Financial Emergency is under operation, the Union is empowered to ", "answer" : " Reduce the salaries of its employees  "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "The three types of Proclamation of Emergency made by the President have to be placed before each House of Parliament for its approval within ", "answer" : "  One month in case of National  Emergency and within two months due to breakdown of constitutional machinery and  Financial Emergency  "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "Which one of the following emergencies can be declared by the President only on the receipt in writing of the decision of the Union Cabinet ", "answer" : "  Emergency due to war,  external aggression or armed rebellion  "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "When a Financial Emergency is proclaimed ", "answer" : " Salaries and allowances of any class of employees may be reduced  "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "If State fails to comply with the directives of the Central Government, the President can ", "answer" : "  declare breakdown of the constitutional machinery in the State and assume  responsibility for its governance  "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "This is not a ground to declare State Emergency ", "answer" : "  No clear majority "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "When a State Emergency is declared, all or any of the functions of the State Government are assumed by the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "President made a Proclamation of Emergency on grounds of internal disturbances for first time in ", "answer" : " 1975  "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "When the State Emergency is in operation, the President can’t interfere in the matters of ", "answer" : " State Judiciary  "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "Who has the duty to protect States against external aggression and internal disturbance? ", "answer" : "  Union Government  "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "For first time, the President make a Proclamation of Emergency under the Article 352  in ", "answer" : " 1962   IX. ELECTORAL PROCESS "},
{ "id" : 1, "question" : "The Electoral System of India is largely based on the pattern of ", "answer" : "   Britain "},
{ "id" : 2, "question" : "The details regarding the Electoral System of India  ", "answer" : "  were provided by the Parliament through a number of laws  "},
{ "id" : 3, "question" : "Who has the power to make necessary provisions with respect to elections? ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 4, "question" : "Who is competent to declare the elections to the Lok Sabha? ", "answer" : "  President "},
{ "id" : 5, "question" : "What is the outstanding feature(s) of the Electoral System of India? ", "answer" : " (i) Political parties are an indispensable part of the process, (ii) Based on Universal Adult Franchise, &  (iii) Provides a single electoral body  "},
{ "id" : 6, "question" : "Elections to Lok Sabha and Legislative Assembly in India are conducted on the basis of ", "answer" : " Adult Franchise  "},
{ "id" : 7, "question" : "What is the system used to elect the President of India? ", "answer" : "  Proportional Representation  "},
{ "id" : 8, "question" : "Who is authorized to determine the territorial constituencies after each Census? ", "answer" : " Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 9, "question" : "Which of the following provisions kept democracy alive in India? ", "answer" : "  Electoral provisions  "},
{ "id" : 10, "question" : "Chief Minister of a State is not eligible to vote in the Presidential Election if he is ", "answer" : " -  Member of the Legislative Council of the State Legislature  "},
{ "id" : 11, "question" : "Voting age of citizens is changed from 21 to 18 years by ____ Constitutional Amendment Act. ", "answer" : " 61st  "},
{ "id" : 12, "question" : "61st Constitutional Amendment reduced the voting age from ", "answer" : " 21 to 18 "},
{ "id" : 13, "question" : "Citizen of India have the right to cast his vote after attaining the age of _____ years. ", "answer" : " -  18  "},
{ "id" : 14, "question" : "Elections in India are held on the basis of ", "answer" : "  Single-member constituencies "},
{ "id" : 15, "question" : "The Chief Election Commissioner ", "answer" : "  Appointed by the President "},
{ "id" : 16, "question" : "The Chief Election Commissioner holds Office ", "answer" : "  for a fixed term of five years "},
{ "id" : 17, "question" : "The number of Members in Election Commission including the Chairman is ", "answer" : " 3  "},
{ "id" : 18, "question" : "Which Article under the Constitution gives power to Election Commission to conduct elections? ", "answer" : " 324  "},
{ "id" : 19, "question" : "The control and preparation of electoral rolls for Parliament and State Legislature vest with the ", "answer" : " Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 20, "question" : "Election to Local Self Government shall be conducted by ", "answer" : "  State Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 21, "question" : "Who will conduct the elections to posts of President and Vice President? ", "answer" : " Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 22, "question" : "Election Commission does not conduct election to ", "answer" : " Speaker of Lok Sabha "},
{ "id" : 23, "question" : "Who has been made responsible for free and fair elections in the country? ", "answer" : "  Chief Election Commissioner  "},
{ "id" : 24, "question" : "Elections to Lok Sabha shall be held after every ", "answer" : " Five years "},
{ "id" : 25, "question" : "For election to Lok Sabha, nomination papers can be filed by ", "answer" : "  Any citizen whose name appears in the electoral roll  "},
{ "id" : 26, "question" : "The party system in India can be described as ", "answer" : " Multi-party "},
{ "id" : 27, "question" : "Which one of the following is a feature of the party system in India? ", "answer" : "  There is a close resemblance in the policies and programmes of various political  "},
{ "id" : 28, "question" : "In India, the citizens have been given the right to vote on the basis of ", "answer" : " age "},
{ "id" : 29, "question" : "Which categories of persons are not entitled to exercise vote through postal ballot? ", "answer" : "  Indian nationals settled abroad  "},
{ "id" : 30, "question" : "Which body gives recognition to political parties? ", "answer" : "  Election Commission "},
{ "id" : 31, "question" : "Main consideration which prompted government to convert Election Commission into a multi-member body was ", "answer" : "  To check the unbridled powers of the Chief Election  Commissioner  "},
{ "id" : 32, "question" : "Who accords recognition to various political parties as national or regional parties? ", "answer" : "  Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 33, "question" : "To be recognized as a national party, a party must secure at least ", "answer" : "  4% of the valid votes in four or more States  "},
{ "id" : 34, "question" : "To be recognized as a regional party, a party must secure at least ", "answer" : "  4% of the valid votes in State  "},
{ "id" : 35, "question" : "Which one of the following statements about the Election Commission is correct? ", "answer" : " The Members of the Election Commission have equal powers with the Chief Election  Commissioner  "},
{ "id" : 36, "question" : "Which of the following is not the function of the Election Commission? ", "answer" : " Selecting candidates for contesting elections  "},
{ "id" : 37, "question" : "This is not the function of the Election Commission. ", "answer" : "  Ascertain the suitability of candidates  "},
{ "id" : 38, "question" : "Election disputes shall be decided by the ", "answer" : " Election Commission "},
{ "id" : 39, "question" : "In terms of Election laws in India, electioneering ceases in a constituency at least ____hours before the commencement of the polling. ", "answer" : " 48  "},
{ "id" : 40, "question" : "The Election Commission does not conduct election to the ", "answer" : " Post of Prime Minister  "},
{ "id" : 41, "question" : "The Election Commission has no power to conduct election to the ", "answer" : " Speaker of Lok Sabha  "},
{ "id" : 42, "question" : "The Election Commission is responsible for the conduct of elections to ", "answer" : " (i) Parliament, (ii) Offices of President and Vice President & (iii) State Legislatures  "},
{ "id" : 43, "question" : "The Election Commission of India enjoys ", "answer" : "  Constitutional basis "},
{ "id" : 44, "question" : "The Election Commission generally consists of the Chief Election Commissioner and such other Commissioners as ", "answer" : "  determined by the President from time to time  "},
{ "id" : 45, "question" : "Chief Election Commissioner can be removed from Office before the expiry of the term by the ", "answer" : "  President on the recommendation of the Parliament  "},
{ "id" : 46, "question" : "Chief Election Commissioner shall be removed by the ", "answer" : " Parliament "},
{ "id" : 47, "question" : "Who of the following has voting rights? ", "answer" : "  Adult resident citizen of a State "},
{ "id" : 48, "question" : "Who is responsible for keeping the voters’ list up-to-date at all times? ", "answer" : "  Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 49, "question" : "The first general elections were held in India in (OR) When did first General Elections was held? ", "answer" : " 1951-52  "},
{ "id" : 50, "question" : "Which of the following General Elections of India was spread over for 100 days? ", "answer" : " First  "},
{ "id" : 51, "question" : "Which of the following features of the Electoral System of India ? ", "answer" : " (i) It is based on Universal Adult Franchise, (ii) Political parties are an indispensable part of the electoral  process  & (iii) It provides a single electoral body  "},
{ "id" : 52, "question" : "The term ‘Fourth Estate’ refers to ", "answer" : " Press "},
{ "id" : 53, "question" : "The chief merit of proportional representation is ", "answer" : "  representation to all parties in the legislature according to their strength  "},
{ "id" : 54, "question" : "In India, the system of proportional representation by means of single transferable vote is used in the election of the ", "answer" : " President  "},
{ "id" : 55, "question" : "Regional Election Commissioners may be appointed by the ", "answer" : " President "},
{ "id" : 56, "question" : "Regional Election Commissioners may be appointed by the President with the consultation of ", "answer" : "  Election Commission  "},
{ "id" : 57, "question" : "Other Election Commissioner or Regional Election Commissioners shall be removed on the recommendation of the ", "answer" : " Chief Election Commissioner  "},
{ "id" : 58, "question" : "Which of the following Lok Sabha was dissolved before the expiry of its nominal term and fresh elections held before the due date? ", "answer" : "  Fourth  "},
{ "id" : 59, "question" : "The Parliamentary elections of 1999, which have been described as the longest elections of India, were spread over _______ weeks. ", "answer" : "  four  "},
{ "id" : 60, "question" : "Which one of the following regional party emerged as the largest opposition party in the Lok Sabha elections held in December, 1984?  ", "answer" : "  Telugu Desam Party  "},
{ "id" : 62, "question" : "What is the ground on which the Chief Election Commissioner of India can be removed from his Office? ", "answer" : "  Incapacity  "},
{ "id" : 63, "question" : "Elections to the Lok Sabha and Legislatives Assemblies in India are held on the basis of ", "answer" : " Adult Franchise"}]